===
===
Music playing
Music playing
Central Research Institute, October's intellectual lecture, the lecture will begin.
Central Research Institute, October's intellectual lecture, the lecture will begin.
Let's welcome Wang Yu-Yi, vice president of the committee.
Let's welcome Wang Yu-Yi, vice president of the committee.
Applause
Applause
Good evening, everyone.
Good evening, everyone.
We are very happy to welcome you.
We are very happy to welcome you.
The director of our Institute of Chemistry is also a researcher
我們本院化學所的所長也是研究員
Director Chen Yuru
陳宇如所長
Then Chen Yuru was in 1992
那陳宇如是1992年
very young
非常年輕
Graduated from the Department of Chemistry, National Taiwan University in 1992
1992年台灣大學化學系畢業
Then I got a Ph.D. in Iowa State in 1997
然後在97年Iowa State拿到博士
Then go back... worked as a Poster in AMS for a year
然後回...在AMS當過一年的Postar
Then I went back to Tsinghua University and worked as a Poster for a year
然後回到清華做了一年Postar以後
to Academia Sinica
就到中研院
So the Academia Sinica has been here since 1999
所以在中研院從1999年就開始在這裡
Then in 2013 he took over as the director of the Institute of Chemistry
然後2013年他就接了化學所的所長
It is also in our Academia Sinica
也是我們中研院裡面
This few very young
這個少數的非常年輕的
Possibly the youngest director
可能是最年輕的所長
also one of the records
也是紀錄之一
Today I see everyone...
今天我看大家...
So excited, there are some high school or junior high school students present
這麼興奮還有一些高中還是國中的學生在場
This topic is obviously very attractive
這個講題顯然非常的受吸引
he is protein
他是蛋白質體
Protonax
Protonax
this protein body
這個蛋白質體
in the last 10 years 20 years
在最近的10年 20年
It's a very, very popular subject.
算是非常非常熱門的一門學問
this
這個
Academia Sinica is also good or
中研院也好或者是
various universities
各個大學
A lot of effort has been spent on this
在這個方面都花了很大的力氣
Chenbai City in
陳柏市在
is used
是用
Probably he will mention it later in his speech
大概待會他的演講裡面也會提
He uses height
他是利用高度的
highly sensitive
高靈敏的
Phytograph
植普儀
Come
來
do this
做這個
Be firm and wait
堅定也好等等
that app is personalizing
那應用是在個人化
Ling Chuang Proteomics
靈闯蛋白質體學
that hope is practical
那希望是在實務上
We can detect diseases early and
我們可以早期發現疾病跟
That is to say, what it actually does
就是說其實它做的東西
from basic chemistry
可以從基本的化學
from the lowest molecular
從最底層的分子
to understand the causes of disease
去了解疾病的原因
In the end we hope to be able to
最後我們是希望能夠
reach individual therapy and more
達到個人治療等等
So I guess this is also
所以我想這個也是
where so many people are interested
有這麼多人有興趣的地方
So its research actually
所以它的研究其實
Across chemical biochemical materials, etc.
跨了化學生化材料等等
is rare
是難得的
We say across many, many fields
我們說跨很多很多領域
and so today it is again
然後所以今天它又是
in the general public
在就一般大眾
It should also be possible to understand what it is doing
應該也可以了解它在做
So he's not just in his own
所以他不只是在他自己的
In Taiwan, apart from our own people,
我們台灣除了自己的人就之外
Of course, what I just said is responsible for some administrative work.
當然我剛剛也講的負責一些行政工作
and some academic service work
還有一些學術的服務工作
For example, learn, etc.
譬如說學會等等
These must also cover some international organizations
這些也一定也cover到國際上的一些組織
So he is also very active internationally
所以他在國際上也非常的活躍
Of course it will take a lot of time
當然也就要花很多很多時間
So we have to stand with him for another two hours today
所以我們今天又要站他兩個鐘頭的時間
I will stop talking nonsense
我就廢話少說
Let Dr. Chen start his speech
就請陳博士開始他的演講
Colleagues in the hospital
各位院內同仁
Hello, everyone outside the hospital.
還有各位院外的來賓大家好
First of all, I would like to thank Vice President Wang for his introduction.
首先先謝謝王副院長的介紹
Actually today I
其實我今天
very very nervous today
今天非常非常緊張
And I've actually been making slideshows for the past few days
然後我這幾天其實一直在做投影片
Because I actually gave a lot of speeches outside in the past
因為我在過去我其實在外面講了非常多的演講
But most of them are aimed at people in the field of science
可是大部分是針對就是科學領域的人
At most, it may be aimed at primary school students, middle school students and college students
那最多就是可能針對小學生、中學生和大學生
and high school students
還有高中生
But when I received this invitation
可是當我接到這個邀請的時候
They told me that they hope to be able to help the general public
他們跟我說希望能夠對於一般社會的大眾
that the general public can
就是一般的民眾能夠
Even people who don't understand our science or biology
即使是不懂我們科學或不懂生物的人
can make them understand
都能夠讓他們懂
It's a big, big challenge for me
對我來講是一個很大很大的挑戰
So I actually spent a lot of thinking these days
所以我這幾天其實花了蠻多想
It's just a lot of thinking
就是蠻多一直在思考說
How can I put this very new theme
怎麼樣能夠把這個很新的一個主題
able to communicate
能夠傳達出去
then i think i will try my best
那我想我會盡力
And let me declare
還有先聲明一下
I am in the chemistry department of National Taiwan University this afternoon
我今天下午在台大化學系
I've been in class for three hours
已經上了三個小時的課
So wait a minute in case the throat breaks
所以等一下萬一喉嚨破風
Please include more
請大家多多的包含
If you have a question, you are welcome to raise your hand anytime
那如果你有問題就是歡迎你隨時舉手
then i miss everyone
那我想大家
when thinking about the average person's perception of protein
在思考一般人對於蛋白質
what is the idea
想法到底是什麼
Then I did a little test
然後我就去做了一個小小的測試
I just type protein into that Google
我就把蛋白質輸入到那個Google裡面去
Then check the picture
然後查圖片
I found out a lot of food
我發現出來一大堆都是食物
It's not a test
就不是什麼檢測啊
nor treatment
也不是治療
all food
全部都是食物
What high protein, low protein
什麼高蛋白質、低蛋白質
good protein bad protein
好的蛋白質、不好蛋白質
So if we take this angle
所以我們如果就這個角度
I'm also starting to think
我也在開始思考說
Why the World Health Organization
為什麼世界衛生組織
List this protein as the main nutrient for humans
把這個蛋白質列為人類主要的營養
I don't know if you have thought about this problem
不知道大家有沒有去想過這個問題
Eating nutrition does not mean
營養吃進去並不是說
You can transform it right away
你馬上就能夠去轉化它
that for protein
那對蛋白質來講
Actually this is a
其實這個是一個
very important source of human health
非常重要的人類健康的來源
because we ate these foods
因為我們吃了這些食物
This protein is broken down into amino acids
這個蛋白質會被分解成胺基酸
Amino acids are a
胺基酸是針對人體一個
the most important ingredient
最重要的一個成分
why
為什麼呢
they will make protein
他們會去組成蛋白質
Then our human body has so many vital functions
那我們的人體會有這麼多的生命功能
Can eat and drink Lassa, can think, can do many, many things
會吃喝拉沙 會思考 會做很多很多事情
In fact, there is a lot of protein to do all kinds of things
其實是有非常多的蛋白質去做各式各樣的事情
including the structure of your body
包括你的身體的結構
why can i move my hands
為什麼我手能動
then includes substance delivery
然後包括物質輸送
then include your metabolism
然後包括你的代謝
You can even think, message transfer, immune regulation, etc.
甚至你能夠思想 訊息傳遞 免疫調節等等
These are all proteins to do the job
這些全部都是蛋白質來做這件事情
But if we look at this biological
可是如果我們來看這個生物學裡面
a so-called one most central criterion
一個所謂一個最中心的一個準則
We know that the most primitive is from DNA
我們知道最原始是從DNA開始
This molecule starts
這個分子開始
that DNA it will turn into RNA
那DNA它會轉入成RNA
RNA is turning into protein
RNA在轉移成蛋白質
that in this deep protein process
那在這個深層蛋白質的過程
It is actually a very complicated process
其實是一個非常複雜的一個過程
in the process
在這個過程之中
There are many factors that make protein expression
會有很多因素讓蛋白質表現量
let me explain
我這邊解釋一下
The so-called performance refers to the
所謂表現量就是指
Concentration meaning
濃度的意思
its concentration will change
它濃度會改變
But in the protein factory
可是在蛋白質這個工廠
in the process of being manufactured
被製造完成的過程中
It will also have a so-called post-repression modification
它會還有一個所謂的轉抑後修飾
It might add, for example in this example
它可能會加上譬如說以這個例子
under the action of some enzymes
在一些酵素的作用之下
protein will be added with some chemical
蛋白質會被加上一些化學的
light energy machine
光能機
For example, this is a
譬如說這個是一個叫
a chemical molecule of pro-acid
臨酸的一個化學分子
After adding these light energy machines
那加上這些光能機之後
It's as if these proteins are spliced
就好像這些蛋白質被接上了
so-called antenna
所謂的天線
It will be identified by many, many actions
它會被很多很多的行動來做辨識
Then we can't help but ask a question
那我們不禁要問一個問題
Among so many biomolecules
在這麼多的生物分子中
who is the most important thing
誰是最重要的事情
who is primarily to perform the function of the organism
誰是主要去執行這個生物的功能
Is it DNA?
是DNA嗎
Is it RNA or protein?
還是RNA 還是蛋白質
I don't announce the answer
我先不宣布答案
please think about it
請大家想一想
Let's start with an interesting question
我們先來回答一個有趣的問題
i like reading philosophy
我很喜歡讀哲學
I have read many theories
那我有看過很多的理論
what is human existence
人的存在到底是什麼
is the physical existence
是肉體的存在
or are you in fact just everything invisible
還是你事實上只是一切都是無形的
just you see this guy
只是你看到這個人
Just an image of your brainwaves
只是你腦波的一個成像
So the biologists
那就生物學家來講
What they must believe is the so-called
他們一定相信的是所謂
Balvin's theory of evolution
巴爾文的進化論
This is the person from this
這個是人是從這個
Slowly evolve from the source
源頭慢慢進化來
But if you are religious
可是如果你是宗教的人
you may feel god
你可能會覺得上帝
He is the biggest commander
才是最大的那個指揮官
God created everything
上帝創造了所有的一切
create everything
創造萬物
I also read science books
我也讀過科學的書
He said that some people think that in fact many
他說有人認為事實上很多的
Our physical existence is a TV wave
我們的身體的存在是一個電視波
There's just one brain center to direct
只是有一個腦中心去指揮
so we're going to answer
所以我們要去回答
who am i
我是誰這個問題
the simplest
最單純的
What we learned from textbooks
我們從教科書裡面學到的
Everyone agrees
大家都認定說
The origin of life is from DNA
生命的起源是來自於DNA
DNA is actually a very mysterious combination
DNA事實上是一個很奧妙的組合
It only has four monomer ATGCs in total
它總共只有四個單體ATGC
But these four monomers
可是這個四個單體
will become tangled into very
會纏繞成變成很
a very long molecule
很長很長的一個一段分子
Then in order to solve this problem
那為了去解決這個解開這個問題
In fact, in the past ten or twenty years
其實在過去一二十年來
There's a very, very important scientific advance
有一個非常非常重要的科學進展
then let me introduce to you
那我為各位介紹一下
If we look at the composition of a person
如果我們來看一個人的組成
we know everyone
我們知道每一個人
you have about six trillion cells
你有大概六兆個細胞
Each person has twenty-three pairs of chromosomes
那每一個人有二十三對染色體
Twenty-two pairs of normal chromosomes
其中有二十二對是一般的染色體
The other pair are the so-called sex chromosomes
另外一對是所謂的性染色體
Then your chromosomes usually come from your mother
那你的染色體一般來自你媽媽
usually from your dad
一般來自你爸爸
But have you ever thought about a question
可是你有沒有去想過一個問題
if this your chromosome
如果這個你的染色體
All from Mom and Dad
全部都來自爸爸跟媽媽
Why Siblings Are So Different
為什麼兄弟姊妹差異很大
regardless of intelligence
不管聰明才智
regardless of your appearance
不管你的外表外型
In fact, many brothers and sisters are not alike at all.
其實很多的兄弟姊妹一點都不像
Then in order to understand this problem
那為了要去了解這個問題
around 1988
在一九八八年左右
Please go back to that long time ago in history
請大家回到那個歷史很早以前
At that time it didn't matter
那個時候還沒有什麼所謂
There is this concept of computer
有這個計算機這個概念
Then in the 1980s
然後在1980幾年那個年代
Gene sequencing work begins
基因定序的工作開始出來
So, some people started to think
那所以呢就有人開始思考說
Now that I can sequence the genes
既然我可以把基因定序
i will explain later
我待會會解釋
Then can we put human
那我們可不可以把人類
This complex genome solves it all
這個複雜的基因組全部把它解出來
The idea of ​​Echo
那Echo這個想法的
is a department called the U.S. Department of Energy
是一個叫美國能源部
The U.S. Department of Energy is a
那美國能源部是在美國一個
very very rich research unit
非常非常有錢的研究單位
Okay, when you think about energy, it means oil.
好 你一想看能源就是石油的意思
they are early
他們就是早期
they are doing a lot of drilling for oil
他們是在做很多開採石油
so they will prop up a lot
所以他們會支柱很多
so-called interesting project
所謂有趣的計畫
Even a plan that everyone thinks is impossible
甚至大家覺得不可能的計畫
as long as it's interesting they'll go to the props
只要有趣他們都會去支柱
So in 1988 when
所以在1988年的時候
DOE
有美國能源部
that combines in the United States for this biomedical field
那結合在美國對於這個生醫領域
a very important research institution
一個非常重要的研究機構
National Institutes of Health
叫美國國家衛生研究院
their two units
他們這兩個單位
First started with such an idea
首先開始了這樣的一個想法
Can we take two or three pairs of human chromosomes
我們可不可以把人類二三對的染色體
corresponding to this gene
所對應到這個基因
can you solve it all
可不可以把它全部解出來
Of course everyone thought it was an impossible task at the time.
那當然當時大家覺得這是一個不可能任務
no one thought it would work
沒有人認為會成功
Then this Selera company
那這個Selera公司
It's a private biotech company
這是一個私人的生物科技公司
Then they later showed the possibility of commercial interests
那他們後來在這中間秀到了商業的利益的可能性
So in 1997 they
所以他們在1997年的時候
joined the program
加入了這個計畫
I didn't expect that in the process
那沒有想到在這個過程之中
Everyone can finally solve this problem with gene sequencing
大家用基因定序最後能夠解決這個問題
Then let me explain a little bit here. This is actually a very interesting method.
那我這邊先稍微解釋一下這個其實是一個很有趣的方法
This genetic sequencing is called the submachine gun method.
這個基因定序叫做衝鋒槍法
Sharkoon is that submachine gun
Sharkon就是那個衝鋒槍
Submachine guns in the movie
電影裡面的衝鋒槍
Then his methodology is actually relying on some coal
那他的方法學其實就是靠一些煤
This coal is also a protein
這個煤也是一個蛋白質
That coal is like a submachine gun
那這個煤就像衝鋒槍一樣
He only sees only DNA
他只看到只要看到DNA
he cut it up
他就把它亂切
So why is he called submachine gun method
所以他為什麼叫衝鋒槍法
that in the process of chopping and chopping
那在亂切亂切的過程之中
i just mentioned
我剛剛有提到
The era sequenced
那個時代定序
This methodology for gene sequencing just came out
基因定序的這個方法學正好出來
so what
所以呢
As long as we can get this
我們只要能夠把這個
The sequence of each small fragment solves it
每一個小片段的序列把它解出來
it has many many many paragraphs
它有很多很多很多段
OK, after I solve it
好 那我解出來之後
I then find out which fragments are overlapping
我再去找哪一些片段是重疊的
or if the same
或者是如果是同一條的話
There should be a part of the sequence that should be repeated
應該有一部分的序列應該是重複的
So you by this example
所以你由這個例子
you can see this paragraph
你可以看到這一段
There are 4 ACGAs here
這邊有ACGA4個
It is the same as the following ACGA4
和下面ACGA4個是一樣的
So it is possible that this paragraph will be connected with this paragraph.
所以有可能這一段跟這一段是要接起來
In the same way, I can put the same
那同理我可以把這邊一樣的
I'll pick it up again
我再把它接起來
So using these three paragraphs
所以利用這三段
I can piece together a long paragraph
我就可以拼湊出長長的一段
by analogy
那依使類推
You can push it piece by piece
你可以一段一段一段去推
finally hook it up
最後把它接起來
ok but i want to stress
好 不過我要強調
this is a very long sequence
這是非常長的一個序列
Okay, so here's a lot of multigene sequencing
好 所以這邊用到非常多基因定序的
Biological information beyond tools
工具之外還有生物資訊
computer information
電腦的資訊
In fact, it is a very important one in this project.
其實是這個工程中非常重要的一個
a component
一個component
So bioinformatics was also at that time
所以生物資訊也是在那個時期
Start a lot of this derivative
開始大量的這個衍生出來
Didn't think it was about 15 years
那沒有想到大概15年的時間
We actually sequenced the human genome
竟然我們把這個人類的基因定序完成了
After that, of course, one after another
那後來 當然後來陸陸續續
Some other countries have joined
還有一些國家陸續加入
So later everyone found out that
所以後來大家才發現說
People are so complicated, everyone is different
人這麼複雜 每一個人都不一樣
In fact, he doesn't have that many genes.
其實他的基因並沒有那麼樣的多
About 30,000 functional copies of this gene
大概就是3萬個功能性的這個基因
Then after the gene sequencing is completed
那在這個基因定序完成之後
Many upgrade companies have been produced one after another
陸陸續續產生了很多升級公司
Chip company Gene testing company
晶片公司 基因的檢測公司
everyone thinks
大家就認為說
After this periodic table
這個記週期表之後
I personally think
我個人是覺得
This is probably the most important thing in the history of human science
這個大概是人類的科學史上最重要的一件事
We've solved the genetic jigsaw puzzle
我們把基因的拼圖拼出來了
So everyone thinks that after having this gene
所以大家都覺得有了這個基因之後
Because the gene produces RNA to produce Portin
因為基因產生RNA 產生Portin
After this blueprint we should all things
這個藍圖之後我們應該所有的事情
all problems can be solved
所有的問題都能夠解決
all the secrets we should be able to know
所有的秘密我們都應該能夠知道
why is there life why is there disease
為什麼有生命 為什麼會產生疾病
But is it true?
可是事實是這樣嗎
Then after the genetic sequencing of this human
那在這個人類的基因定序之後
A new field has emerged called genomics
出現了一個新的領域叫做基因體學
Well, the gene is a segment
好 那基因就是一段一段一段
This is called gene
這個叫基因
Genome means
基因體的意思就是說
I'm going to study all the genes, this is called the gene body
我要研究所有的基因 這個叫做基因體
I'm going to learn about all the structures
我要去了解所有的結構
I'm going to find out what it does
我要去了解它的功能
This is called genomics
這個叫做基因體學
Here are some students here to explain
那這邊有一些學生為解釋一下
A gene means a single
基因的話就是代表單一
Then if you see this OME, it means all the components
那如果你看到這個OME就代表所有的組成
This is called GENOME
這個叫做GENOME
Then add ICS to represent the knowledge of what to study
那加上ICS就代表研究什麼什麼的學問
So you'll hear a lot of GENOMICS
所以你會聽到很多GENOMICS
POTENOMICS METAPOLOMICS
POTENOMICS METAPOLOMICS
What do they represent?
都是代表什麼什麼體學
There is even a company in Taiwan called
那甚至台灣現在有一家公司叫
Physical science companies are studying these
體學公司就是在研究這些
Then after the genetic sequencing of this human
那在這個人類的基因定序之後
One after another there are many important
陸陸續續有非常多重要的
The species sequencing of this animal was also done
這個動物的物種的定序也被完成
then you may feel
那大家可能會覺得
why not our cutest puppy
為什麼沒有我們最可愛的小狗啊
cats because they are not animal models
貓啊 因為他們不是動物的模式
Then you can see things like worms, mice, etc.
那你可以看到像現虫 老鼠等等
These are zebrafish
這些都是斑馬魚
These are very important for biomedical research
這些都是非常重要做生醫研究的
an animal pattern
一個動物的模式
So these are sequenced
所以這些都被定序了
In the process, a very interesting question arises
那在這過程中也衍生了一個很有趣的問題
In theory this could be one of the most important discoveries in human history
理論上這個可能是人類史上最重要的發現之一
we make money from it
我們那邊從中間賺錢
And this guy Gray Venter
那這個Gray Venter這個人
is what I just mentioned
就是剛剛我所提到的
The president of this company at Stellera
在Stellera這家公司的總裁
then why did he join
那他為什麼加入
because he finds it profitable
因為他覺得有利可圖
So then he brought up
所以後來他提出來
should go to the result of this sequence
應該要去把這個定序的結果
apply for patent
申請專利
Everyone who wants to use it has to pay
只要要使用的人全部都要付費
That is to believe that he lost
那就是信好他輸了
Because everyone thinks that human genes
因為大家覺得人類的基因
belongs to all
是屬於所有的人
It should not be used for commercial interests
不應該是用這個來做商業的利益
So he lost
所以後來他敗屬
he lost to him
他敗屬他
Everyone thinks it should be shared
大家覺得應該共享
so the same human protein
所以相同的人類蛋白質
Once completed in the future
將來一旦完成
also belong to all mankind
也都是屬於全人類
Everyone in our field feels that
我們這個領域大家共同覺得
This should belong to all mankind
這應該是屬於全人類的這個
a blessing of
的一個福祉
but at the same time
但是在這個同時
He also did a very interesting thing
他也做了一個非常有趣的事情
Then in 2000 when he
那他在2000年年年的時候
publishes his own personal sequence
發表他自己個人的定序
then why did i bring it up
那我為什麼特別提出來
Because after about seven or eight years of this process
因為經過這大概七八年來的這個過程
In fact, the tools for gene sequencing are becoming more and more mature.
其實基因定序的工具越來越成熟
so you can imagine
所以你可以想像到
I personally at least believe
我個人至少我很相信
one day
有一天
You may want to see if there is anything wrong with your body
你可能要看看你身體有沒有什麼狀況
you originally had a gene
你最初有一個基因的
may be able to tell you
也許能夠告訴你
The state of your body now
你現在身體的這個狀況
So this is a very important development
所以這個是一個非常重要的發展
But after gene sequencing is complete
但是基因定序完成之後
do we solve all the problems
我們解決所有的問題嗎
I would like to introduce two important people here
我這邊要介紹兩個重要的人
an important person black star our ten group
一個重要的人黑星星我們的十組
I don't need to introduce
不用我介紹
there is another
還有另外一個
This is my college classmate
這個是我大學同學
Researcher Lin Zhiming
林志明研究員
He is now at the Fate Institute of Academia Sinica
他現在在中研院的緣分所
He is a disciple of Dean Li Yuanzhe
是李遠哲院長的高徒
he is super
他超級厲害
He is doing this in the atmosphere
他是在做這個大氣中
This environment-related molecule
這個跟環境有關的分子
so he is my idol
所以他是我的偶像
My classmates have been great since before
我同學從以前都厲害到現在
Excuse me
請問大家
How similar are these two people
這兩個人相似度多少
don't be afraid
大家不要害怕
I asked Lin Zhiming for permission
我徵求林志明同意過了
so don't be afraid
所以大家不要害怕
Lin Zhiming agreed
林志明同意了
he heard this too
他也聽過這個
I did this
我當初做這件事
Because he first asked me to teach high school students
因為他最早找我去教高中生
I said can I be kidding
我說我可不可以開開玩笑
say no problem
說沒問題
He's so smart that the black star
他絕頂聰明 那黑星星
I think Lin Zhiming is at least much handsomer than him
我想林志明至少比他帥很多
Does anyone want to take a guess please ask you
有沒有人要猜猜看 請問你
How similar are their genes
他們兩個的基因的相似度有多高
99.5
99.5
Then I believe that many people here must have studied statistics.
那我相信這邊一定很多人念過統計的
Is there any student or person who can tell me
有沒有哪一位學生或人能夠告訴我
In the case of statistically two standard deviations
統計上兩個標準差的情況之下
What is the percentage of similarity between two objects
兩個物體相似的百分比是多少
We call these two things the same
我們叫做這兩個東西是一樣的
Can anyone tell me that students should be able to
有沒有人能夠告訴我 學生應該可以
More than 90
90多
how many 90
多少90幾
My students can't answer
我的學生回答不出來
i say it again
我再講一遍
That is to say, statistically we often say
就是說統計上我們常常來說
With a probability of 95.5 percent
機率百分之95.5的機率之下
We call these two things the same
這兩個東西我們就把它叫做一樣
So in statistics, 95.5 is the same as we think
所以在統計上面 95.5是我們認定一樣
So if from this point of view
所以如果從這個角度來講
the answer is 98
答案是98
So from a practical point of view
所以從這個實際的層面來講
98% of human DNA is exactly the same as stars
人類的DNA98%跟星星是一模一樣
Then if you talk about statistics
那你如果套統計來說
they are the same
他們兩個人是一樣
But you know it's totally different
可是你明明知道完全不同
the next question
那下一個問題
if the same person
如果相同的人
How similar is this gene
這個基因的相似度有多少
let me explain
我還是解釋一下
This is the most handsome man in the world in my opinion
這個是我認為全世界最帥的男人
And this is the smartest in the world I think
然後這個是我覺得全世界最聰明的
I adore him so much
我超級崇拜他的
so he is my alien
所以他是我外星人
I also believe
我也很相信
Of course Lin Zhiming is still very good
當然林志明還是很厲害
How similar are these three people?
請問這三個人相似度有多高
We just said that people are 98 times worse than stars
我們剛剛說人跟星星差98
How different are the three
這三個人差異有多少
just that answer
就剛剛那個答案
99.9
99.9
So here comes an interesting question:
所以這邊衍生一個有趣的問題是
the three of them totally
他們三個完全
not related to
跟沒有親緣的關係
but their genes
可是他們的基因
Up to 99.9% similarity
高達99.9%的相似度
So if you and your brothers and sisters
那如果你跟你的兄弟姊妹
you can imagine
你可以想像
You feel more similar
你們的相似度覺得更高
But why are people so different
可是為什麼人這麼不一樣
good
好
Here I list
這邊我列出了
several fragments of genes
幾條片段的基因
one of them
其中有一個人
one of them is
其中有一個人是
The Genes of the Mediterranean Type
地中海形評學的基因
I don't know everyone's eyes
不知道大家眼睛
Can you see the difference?
能不能看得出來哪裡不一樣
one of them is
其中有一條是
mediterranean critique
地中海形評學
different from others
跟別人是不一樣的
here
這裡
good
好
so everyone can see
就大家可以看到
at this place
在這個地方
this place is different
這個地方是不一樣的
good
好
so say
那所以說
genetically similar
基因雖然高度相近
but why
可是為什麼
a defect in a gene or two
一兩個基因的缺陷
on the contrary, it will make a big difference
反而會造成很不一樣
mediterranean typology
譬如說地中海形評學
Then I'll give another one
那我再舉另外一個
more extreme example
更極端的例子
we know say
我們知道說
My biology is not good
這個我生物不太好
But we know that butterflies have
但是我們知道蝴蝶有
From passing through the egg, no, it should be the egg, right?
從經過卵,不對,應該卵,對不對?
egg, from brave to heavy
卵,又從到勇,一直到沉重
it has undergone such a transformation
它經過了一個這麼大的轉變
But if you look at its genome,
可是如果你去看它的基因體的話
The genome of these four periods is completely unchanged
這四個時期的基因體是完全不變
are exactly the same
是一模一樣的
So there seems to be some problem here
所以這邊似乎有一些問題
we are not able to answer
我們不太能夠去回答
it goes through if all the same
它經歷如果都一樣
why is it so different
為什麼它這麼的不一樣
No matter its shape, no matter its whole state
不管是外形,不管是它整個狀態
is completely different
是完全全不一樣的
So in the process
所以在這個過程中
let me explain
讓我來幫各位解釋一下
We know that DNA turns into RNA
我們知道DNA產生轉路變成RNA
that makes protein from RNA
那從RNA產生蛋白質
That's because each DNA transfer process to RNA
那因為這每一個DNA轉路到RNA的過程中
It each this password is fixed
它每一個這個密碼都是固定的
ATGC must be the same for everyone
ATGC這一定每一個都要對一樣的
So theoretically once the DNA is fixed,
所以理論上DNA一旦固定之後
It produces proteins that are also immobilized
它會產生蛋白質也是固定的
Because every RNA code
因為每RNA的code
will produce the same amino acid
會產生同樣的胺基酸
That's why
那以
Just for this example
剛剛這個例子來講
Why did the DNA sequence change after
為什麼那個DNA的序列變了以後
mediterranean selection
會造成地中海形評選
The reason is that
原因就是在於
When this gene is mutated
當這個基因突變的時候
For example, this is a normal gene
譬如說這個是正常的基因
Then these two produce
那這兩個產生出來
should produce this amino acid
應該會產生這個胺基酸
But what happens when your genetic mutation
可是呢當你的基因突變之後
It starts from this amino acid
它從這個胺基酸
into this amino acid of Valorin
變成了Valorin的這個胺基酸
This position happens to be the protein
這個位置正正好是蛋白質
This hemoglobin is combined with oxygen
這個血紅蛋白它是跟氧氣結合
it's in our blood
它在我們的血液之中
is responsible for carrying oxygen
是負責攜帶氧氣
This location happens to be
這個位置正好是
The position where this protein binds to the oxygen species
這個蛋白質跟氧氣分質結合的位置
In other words, the point
換句話說其實重點
because the structure of the protein has changed
是因為蛋白質的結構變掉了
So it produces Mediterranean type selection
所以它產生地中海形評選
So from this example tell us that
所以從這個例子中告訴我們說
Actually the protein it is really going to perform
其實蛋白質它是真正去執行
An important function of a molecule
功能的一個重要的一個分子
genes are stable
基因是穩定的
protein is the active
蛋白質才是那個有活性的
to help you perform functions
去幫你執行的功能
So after genomics
所以在基因體學之後
A new field has emerged
出現了一個新的領域
protein body
叫做蛋白質體
I think I probably know all about protein.
那蛋白質我想大概應該都了解
that proteosome
那蛋白質體
means all protein
意思就是所有的蛋白質
This is called protein body
這個叫做蛋白質體
what about this concept
那這個概念呢
it was 1994
是1994年
by this from Australia
由澳洲的這個
Professor Marco Wilken
Marco Wilken教授
first proposed
首先提出來的
But I'm here to tell you
不過我這邊要跟大家說
when he brought it up
就是他提出來的時候
It's his first year of doctoral class
是他博士班一年級
the age of his students
他學生的年代
So he still looks like this
所以他現在長得還是這樣
This is his current photo
這是他現在的照片
He's younger than me at the right age
他適當年紀比我還輕
The appearance of this proteosome
那這個蛋白體的出現
In fact, he wants to respond
其實他是想要去對應
we want to understand
我們想要去了解
These are the ones that actually perform the function
這些真正執行功能的
these proteins
這些蛋白質
we want to analyze him
我們想要去分析他
So we gave him a
所以我們給了他一個
protein body
叫蛋白體這個名詞
So we want to understand
所以我們想要去了解
all protein
所有的蛋白質
That field is analyzing
那這個領域在分析的
or what are you looking at
或在看的是什麼呢
for example
譬如說
We want to understand the different states
我們想了解不同的狀態之下
Behavior of the protein Has its concentration changed?
蛋白質的表現 它的濃度有沒有發生改變
Especially cancer, which we'll get to later.
尤其癌症我們等一下會提到
Many cancers are caused by protein concentration
很多的癌症都是因為蛋白質濃度
abnormal increase
不正常的增加
or after generation
或者是產生之後
Post-repression modification of this protein
這個蛋白質的轉抑後修飾
Did it add some special light energy machine
它是不是加上了一些特別的光能機
Like Linghua or like Zhongyuanyuan
像凌酸化或者像中原院
a very important area
一個很重要的領域
Glycosylation Glycosylation
糖基化Glycosylation
Added some specific sugar molecules
加上了一些特異的糖分子
The entire protein structure and its function are all changed.
整個蛋白質結構跟它的功能全部都變掉
even protein measurements
甚至是蛋白質的三圍四圍
It is the structure of three degrees and four degrees
就是三度四度的這個結構
And protein is actually very similar to people
還有蛋白質其實跟人很像
According to the research in the project play
根據在項目劇裡面的研究
70% of protein is with other people
蛋白質有70%是跟別人在一起
it doesn't exist alone
它不是單獨存在
like human society
就像人的社會
Then it likes three to five friends best
然後它最喜歡就是三到五個朋友
So in East
所以在East裡面
About three to five proteins are aggregated together
大概三到五個蛋白質都是聚在一起
So this is also a very interesting thing
所以這也是一個很有趣的事情
its not a singles
它不是單一單打
it's actually a group
它其實是一個群體
Let's do something together
大家一起去做一件事情
Let's give an example
我們舉例子
with this history
用這個歷史來看
If you go for a cancer test today
如果你今天去做癌症檢測
Is it DNA?
是DNA嗎?
mostly protein
大部分絕大多數全都是蛋白質
This is where you go to the hospital
這張是你去醫院裡面
during this cancer screening
做這個癌症篩檢的時候的
a some protein
一個一些蛋白質
have some protein
有一些蛋白質
it has high professionalism
它有很高的專業性
For example, this liver cancer
譬如說這個肝癌
Not recommended
Avatitoprotein
This is an embryonic protein
這個是一個胚胎蛋白
when your concentration
當你濃度
this egg white is interesting
這蛋白很有趣
its when a woman is pregnant
它在婦女懷孕的時候
when the fetus
胎兒的時候
This concentration is very high
這個濃度很高
After birth, however, the concentration decreases
可是出生之後濃度下降
But when this protein concentration
但是當這個蛋白質濃度
Just be careful when raising
就在提高的時候你要小心
You are at risk for cancer
你有剛癌這個風險
another prostate cancer
另外一個前列腺癌
There are also relatively specialized proteins
也是有相對比較專業的蛋白質
There are some so-called screening proteins
有一些是所謂篩選性的蛋白質
This is the number of the protein
這個都是蛋白質的編號
that you are in many different
就是你在很多各式各樣的
These concentrations are elevated in cancer
癌症的時候這些濃度都會上升
So the doctor will tell you that in case of misfortune
所以醫生就會跟你說萬一不幸的
Your concentration increases
你這些濃度增加
He'll tell you to watch, screen, etc.
他就會叫你觀察篩選等等
But you can also see from here
但是你從這邊也可以看到
still many important cancers
還是很多重要的癌症
e.g. lung cancer
譬如說肺癌
No detected molecules at all
根本沒有任何的檢測的分子
the other one
那另外一個
just is the detection point of view
剛剛是檢測的觀點
from a therapeutic point of view
那從治療的觀點
Protein is also the most important
蛋白質也是最重要的這個
target molecule
標靶的這個分子
that is outside the sin of the cell
那在細胞的罪外面
we call the top of the cell membrane
我們叫細胞膜上面
on the cell membrane
在細胞膜上面
There are so many important glycoproteins
有非常多重要的這個糖蛋白
Membrane Protein
膜蛋白
then they are often
那他們常常是
double as this material transport
兼任這個物質運送
especially the function of drug delivery
尤其是藥物運送的功能
Then they also receive messages from the outside world.
那他們也是對外接受訊息
And then also they're doing a lot of molecular
然後也是他們在做很多分子
Identify a very important protein
辨識一個非常重要的蛋白質
So if you look at this treatment this statistic
所以如果你去看這個治療這個統計
Let me explain a little bit here
這邊我稍微解釋一下
This is the article
就是這邊文章
he went to count
他去統計了
Probably nearly 500 different drugs in clinical practice
大概在臨床上將近500種不同的藥
Then it counts who these drugs are aimed at.
那它去統計這些藥到底是針對誰
come do this go be a goal
來做這個去當目標
Then you can see that the DNA is very small
那你可以看DNA很小很小一塊
only here
只有在這裡
Everything else is protein
其他全部都是蛋白質
all of them
全部都是
So if you're looking at this receptor
那如果你在看這個receptor
It's a receptor for a receiving protein called messaging
它是一種叫訊息傳遞的接受蛋白質的受體
Those are all cell membrane proteins
那這些全部都是細胞膜膜蛋白
Probably we can say that more than 70% of the drugs
大概我們可以說70%以上的藥物
All target membrane proteins of cell membranes
全部都是以細胞膜的膜蛋白為目標
The most famous one is GPCR
那最有名的就是GPCR
receptor protein
這類的受體蛋白
They are widely used in
他們廣泛的被應用到
various diseases
各式各樣的這個疾病
So from the detection point of view
所以從檢測角度
From a Drug Development Perspective
從藥物開發的角度
Proteins are very important class of molecules
蛋白質都是非常重要的一類分子
that in the process
那在這個過程之中
it actually
它事實上
But it compares to DNA
但是它比起DNA來講
It's actually a very complicated process
它事實上是非常複雜一個過程
Then I have a protein with this
那我以這個有一個蛋白質
It's called EGF
叫EGF啊
This is currently in lung cancer and breast cancer
這個目前是在肺癌跟乳癌裡面
target especially lung cancer
標靶的尤其是肺癌
Most important most important target protein
最重要最重要的標靶的蛋白
So this is a protein structure
那這個是一個蛋白質結構
This circle represents the protein structure
這個圈圈的就代表蛋白質結構
This place represents the cell membrane
這個地方是代表細胞膜
It's a protein stuck in the cell membrane
它是卡在細胞膜上的一個蛋白
that's outside the cell membrane
那在細胞膜的外面
it has a lot of sugar programs
它有非常多的糖計畫
these are sugar
這些都是糖
Then everyone already knows, not everyone
那大家已經知道 不是大家
This is Dean Wen's discovery
這是溫院長的發現
they found out
他們發現說
EGF outside the cell membrane
這個細胞膜外面的EGF啊
If there is this Syllation
如果有這個Syllation
dehydrated acid sugar
這種糖脫液酸糖
or sugar like Fucose
或Fucose這類糖的話
it will suppress
它會去抑制
This EGF
這個EGF啊
This protein is activated
這個蛋白質被活化
That's more complicated
那更複雜的是
outside changed
外面改變了
It actually affects the inside
它事實上也會影響到裡面
The P stands for the message transmission of acidification
這個P就代表臨酸化的訊息傳遞
This is currently the most important mechanism for message delivery
這個是目前最重要訊息傳遞的一個機制
Then they found that once the outside sugar was suppressed
那他們發現一旦外面的糖被抑制了
It also causes EGF
它也會造成EGF啊
The probability that this protein is activated
這個蛋白質被活化的機率
But what is interesting is our experience
但是有趣的是我們的經驗
When Dean Wen told us at that time
溫院長那時候在跟我們說的時候
I think such an important goal
我想這麼重要的目標
Should be clear here
應該這邊都搞清楚
in fact not yet
事實上還沒
so exaggerated
所以很誇張
I think it's exaggerated
我覺得很誇張
Such an important target therapy
這麼重要的一個標靶療法
But the above structure
可是這上面的結構
The underlying structure is currently unclear
這下面的結構目前是不清楚的
How does it affect the two
它到底兩個是怎麼影響
Actually still not clear
事實上還是不清楚
that in terms of it
那以它來講
Why are these targets
為什麼這些標靶
Why These Membrane Proteins Are Important
為什麼這些膜蛋白很重要
because once it is stimulated
因為它一旦被刺激之後
it initiates what is called messaging
它會啟動所謂訊息傳遞
like we're running a relay race
就像我們接力賽跑一樣
protein one by one
蛋白質一個一個接下去
Many times in this race it has to take over
很多時候這個賽跑它要接棒
It is through this spiritual acidification
就是靠這個靈酸化
Once acidified by the spirit it knows
一旦被靈酸化它就知道
I'm coming to take over
我要來接棒
those messages
那這些訊息傳遞
once it happens it's bad
一旦發生了就糟了
sometimes there are some roads
有的時候有一些路
it causes cell growth
它會造成細胞生長
But if cancer cells grow
可是如果是癌細胞生長
that would be bad, cause cancer
那就糟了 產生癌症
so how to find out
所以怎麼樣去瞭解
The process of this message passing
這個訊息傳遞的過程
And then to shoot
進而去射
New drug to inhibit such a pathway
新的藥物來抑制這樣一條路
It's actually a very important point
事實上是一個非常重要的觀點
In terms of acidification
以這個凌酸化這件事情來講
The targeted therapy currently used in hospitals
在目前在醫院裡面所用到的這個標靶療法
You can see all these proteins
你可以看到全部都是這些蛋白
each of these names is protein
這些每個名字都是蛋白質
These are all membrane proteins of the cell membrane
這些全部都是細胞膜的膜蛋白
Some use small molecules to inhibit it
有的是用小分子來抑制它
Some use antibodies to inhibit it
有的是用抗體來抑制它
Let me give you an example
我舉一個例子來講
For example, the method of liquid drama
譬如說液劇的法
this is lung cancer
這個是肺癌
Lung cancer in the East is very different from lung cancer in the West
東方的肺癌跟西方的肺癌非常的不一樣
Lung cancer in the East has a characteristic
東方的肺癌有一個特色
early-onset lung cancer in women
就是早發性的婦女的早發性肺癌
relatively high
相對是比較高
There is another very important feature
還有一個很重要的特色
It is the liquid drama method that the protein will have a so-called mutation
就是液劇的法這個蛋白質會有所謂的突變
it will have this mutation
它會有這個突變
The advantage is that once the method of this liquid drama changes
好處是一旦這個液劇的法突變之後
Add this medicine outside
這個外面加來這個藥
This TKI is a drug
這個TKI是一個藥
Now maybe everyone talks about Aretha
現在可能大家講愛瑞莎
everyone will understand
大家會比較了解
This is a targeted therapy drug for cancer
這個是癌症的標靶療法的藥
The advantage is that once there is a mutation
那好處是一旦有突變之後
These drugs can inhibit their
這些藥對他們可以抑制
so that it doesn't generate this rep suppression
讓它不會產生這個代表抑制
But these patients take medicine
可是這些病人吃藥
After about six months to a year, unfortunately
大概半年到一年之後很不幸的
Almost always produces a second mutation
幾乎都會產生第二次的突變
The second mutation of this place
這個地方第二次的突變
Bad once mutated
一旦突變之後糟糕了
They eventually develop resistance
他們最後就產生抗藥性
So it will recur in the end
所以最後還是會復發
Then this is still the oriental lung
那這個目前還是東方肺
an unsolvable problem
一個無解的問題
There is still no way
目前還是沒辦法
So from this point of view
所以從這個觀點
you can understand
你可以了解
protein is a
蛋白質是一個
In fact, it is a very complicated mechanism
其實是一個很複雜的一個機制
Then we have to understand the whole process well.
那我們只有好好的去了解這整個過程
We can devise new methods and strategies
我們才能夠設計新的方法跟策略
to understand the process
來了解這個過程
The most complicated thing is that it is not a single path
那最複雜的是它不是單一條路
It's called all roads lead to Rome
它是所謂的條條大路通羅馬
In terms of medical cancer law
以醫療癌法來講
this is a cell
這個是一個細胞
It has at least three, four or more
它至少有三條、四條以上
different way
不一樣的路
In other words
換句話
Say your cancer is treated today
話說你癌症今天治療
you stuck this road
你把這條路卡死了
Today, the Central Plains Court closed this road
我今天中原院封了這條路
I can also get from Southport
我還可以從南港
from another direction
從另外一個方向
or from that highway
或從那個高速公路
I go shopping in Sogo
我到Sogo去買東西
there are so many roads
有非常多的路
So how can these systems
所以怎麼樣能夠去把這些系統
able to figure out
能夠搞清楚
I personally think it is very important
我個人覺得是非常重要
Because in traditional protein research
因為在傳統的蛋白質研究
Usually it is to study a Protin
通常就是研究一個Protin
But it's actually a systemic problem
可是它其實是一個系統的問題
Then I use this example
那我用這張例子
It's easier to understand when you explain it to everyone
解釋給大家聽比較容易理解
I'm here
我在這裡
Nakahara Institute expects
那中原院期待
Each of us should do a good job in research
我們每個人研究要做得好
well done research
那研究做得好
My students, I just take out two of them
我的學生我隨便拿兩個人出來
most related to me
跟我最有關係
In theory, my students should work hard and earnestly.
理論上是我學生努力認真就好了
But is it actually so?
可是事實上是這樣嗎
no
不行
because in this study
因為在這個研究中
There are so many tools that I can't have
有非常多的工具我沒有辦法有
so i have to rely on others
所以我必須要靠別人
This is Mr. Song Yifei from the Information Office
就是這個是資訊所的宋定義老師
ok then this is my friend from japan
好 那這是我日本一個朋友
Mr. Yixu Hama, Kyoto University
一序哈瑪老師 京都大學
So in fact, I have to do a good job in research
所以其實我研究要做得好
can't just look at them
不能只看他們
Then if I want to study lung cancer
那我如果要研究肺癌
I did not visit the pier with Principal Yang Panchi
我沒有去跟楊潘池校長拜碼頭
probably not too good
大概也不太OK
Because he knows best what lung cancer is
因為他最知道肺癌是什麼問題
So this is a very important alliance
所以這個是一個很重要的聯盟
But if research funding is concerned
可是如果研究經費來講
This is Dean Wen, everyone should know
這是溫院長大家應該認識
Then the deputy king is here
然後這王副在這裡
So if I tell this next joke to only
那如果我接下來這個笑話講給只有
Finally someone understands
終於有一點人在聽得懂了
just if you're going to ask for money
就是如果你要去要錢
No one will ask the dean
沒有人會去跟院長要
Because you want your self-esteem not to suffer
因為你希望自尊心不要受損
hope you feel better
希望心情好一點
Usually we go to the smiling person and ask
通常我們就會去跟微笑的人要
then vice wang
那就王副
Then we will ask the dean for money as a last resort.
那不得已我們才會去跟院長要錢
And of course but so what I'm going to say is
然後當然但是所以我要講的是
This is just a working network
這個只是一個工作的網路
In other words, if you are going to ask today
換句話說今天如果大家要去問
Can Chen Yuru do research well at Academia Sinica?
陳玉如在中研院能不能把研究做好
It's not my problem
其實不是我一個人的問題
It is a very complex network problem
是非常複雜的一個網路的問題
If you want to ask today
那如果今天要問說
I will give another simple example
我再舉一個簡單的例子
For example, let's say we're getting married
譬如說我們說要結婚
Then you have a girlfriend, boyfriend
那你交了一個女朋友、男朋友
you have to predict
你要去預測
you marry him in the future
你跟他將來結婚
Will you be happy
會不會幸福美滿
you absolutely need to know his family
你絕對要了解他的家庭
right
對不對
For example, you want to know your mother-in-law
譬如說你要了解你的婆婆
Will it be difficult to get along with?
會不會很難相處啊等等等
So this is a
所以這個是一個
complex network problem
複雜的一個網路問題
OK, so we think protein
好 所以我們認為蛋白質
with proteosomes
跟蛋白質體
In fact, only through the proteosome
事實上只有透過蛋白質體
In order to be able to understand more systematically
才能夠去比較有系統的去了解
what happened to us
我們發生了什麼事情
at the molecular level
在分子的層次上面
The first big obstacle is
那第一個遇到的大障礙就是
The protein body is so complex
蛋白質體這麼的複雜
what tools are we going to use for research
我們要用什麼工具來做研究
Let's start with the simplest species
那我們先從這個最簡單的物種
Even a simple E. coli
即使是一個簡單的大腸桿菌
it has thousands of proteins
它都有幾千個蛋白質
Then we estimate human
那我們預估人類
There are at least 35,000 different
至少有三萬五千個不一樣的
different protein
不一樣的蛋白質
What tool can be used to do this
用什麼工具才能來做這件事
So how do we identify proteins
那我們要怎麼去鑑定蛋白質
that identifies proteins in this
那在這個鑑定蛋白質
what i call identification
我所謂的鑑定
I put this definition first
我把這個定義先說進去
not that i need to know this
並不是說我要知道這個
i am female
我是女的
I want the so-called identification is
我要所謂鑑定是
you have to tell me
你必須要告訴我
I am Chen Yuru
我是陳裕儒
I am not Wang Qihui
我不是汪啟慧
I'm not Vice President Wang Yu, etc.
我不是汪漁副院長等等等
This is called identification
這個叫做鑑定
so as a tool
所以當一個工具
how to tell you this
怎麼去告訴你這件事呢
The paper spectrometer is here
那紙譜儀在這個
It's a tool that's over a hundred years old
這是一個超過一百年的工具
that from the earliest atoms in our periodic table
那從最早在原子我們的周期表
wait a minute we'll talk
等一下我們會講
OK, let's talk about this first
好 我們先講這邊
Then this paper spectrometer
那這個紙譜儀
It's actually a stick
它其實就是一個棒稱
It can tell your analyte
它可以告訴你的分析物
How much does it weigh
到底有多重
Its concept is actually very simple
那它的概念其實非常的單純
Its concept is
它的概念就是
When we charge the analyte
當我們把分析物讓它帶電的時候
under the action of a power plant or a magnetic field
在電廠或磁場的作用之下
the time it arrived at the detector
它到達偵測器的時間
Or the path will be different
或者是路徑會不一樣
So we can use this way
所以我們可以透過這樣的方式
to measure the quality
去測出來這個質量的
the size of this
這個的大小
it's complicated
那它很複雜
i guess i won't explain
我想我就不去解釋
It's a very complex instrument
這是一個非常複雜的儀器
In fact, everyone is very concerned about Zhi Puyi
那其實大家對於脂朴衣
It shouldn't feel too strange
應該是不會感到太陌生
Because the first periodic table
因為第一個周期表
is the first
就是第一個
For the first element of the periodic table
就周期表第一個元素
It is measured from the concept of fat
就是從脂朴這個概念去測出來的
If you still remember this JJ Thompson
那如果大家還記得這個JJ Thompson
He was the first to discover that
他是首先發現說
in this power plant
在這個電廠之中
We'll see a so-called charged one
我們會看到一個所謂帶電的一個
a radiation
一個輻射
In fact, it is a lipo
事實上那就是一個脂朴
So this is the earliest and earliest Zhipu
所以這個是最早期最早期的一個脂朴
You can see this atom of Niang
大家可以看到尼昂的這個原子
it has two parity digits
它有兩個同位數
20 and 22
20跟22
because its weight is different
因為它的重量不一樣
So it's under this action of this magnetic field
所以它在這個磁場的這個作用之下
it deflects
它產生了偏摺
This is a lipo
這是一個脂朴
So using this simple concept
所以利用這個脂朴的概念
we can build
我們可以得以建立
This human this is probably the human always the ultimate
這個人類這大概是人類始終最終
The most important thing is the periodic table
最重要的一件事就是周期表
However, although Zhipu has been
可是植普雖然在一百年來
so widely used
用的這麼廣泛
But in the early days
可是在早期的時候
Actually none of us ever knew
其實我們從來沒有人知道
He can do biomolecular analysis
他可以做生物分子的分析
In the development of this whole history, this Zhipu
這個植普在這個整個歷史的發展中
from the earliest atoms
從最早的原子
then to the chemical age
然後到化學年代
many, many small molecules
很多很多的小分子
until the 1970s
一直到1970年代
Polymer oil extraction and so on
高分子石油開採等等等等
carried on until later
一直推展到後來
what about later
那後來呢
around 1995
在1995年左右
By Mr. Tanaka from Japan
由日本這個Tanaka先生
He's an engineer from Xu Ma's company
他是一個許媽子公司的工程師
Then when he was doing an experiment
那他在做一次實驗的時候
That era was the age of polymers
那個年代是高分子時代
So his task is to find a material
所以他的任務就是必須要找出一個材料
Let this polymer be our textile
讓這個高分子就是我們的紡織
plastic these
塑膠這些
Can be tested with Zhipu
能夠用植普去測
How big is this polymer?
到底這個高分子有多大
then he made a mistake once
那他有一次做錯
Accidentally discovered the world's first protein map
無意中發現了全世界第一張蛋白質的圖譜
Then its method is to use the concept of laser
那它的方法是利用雷射這個概念
To do the identification of this mass spectrum
來做這個質譜的鑒定
Then there is another professor John Fenn
那另外有一位John Fenn教授
He has always hoped to use high-voltage electricity
他一直希望用高壓的電
able to make this deepening molecule
能夠讓這個深化分子
be able to electrify it to be detected
能夠讓它帶電進而去被檢測到
So he's using a method called electrospraying
所以他是利用一個叫做電噴灑的方法
It's the high voltage that sprays it out
就是高電壓把它噴出來
the two of them
那他們兩個
discovered at almost the same time
同時在幾乎在同時間都發現了
for this protein molecule
對這個蛋白質分子
capable of mass spectrometry
能夠去做質譜的分析
So in 2002 when they
所以他們在2002年的時候
Received the Nobel Prize in Chemistry
拿到了諾貝爾的化學獎
Then this is in this field
那這個是在這個領域中
a very important development
一個非常重要的一個發展
Then I'll pick one of the easy ones first.
那我先挑其中一個簡單的方法
explain to everyone
解釋給大家聽
Why can mass spectrometry measure this mass?
為什麼質譜可以去測這個質量的
this size
這個大小
Then what I introduce here is
那我這邊介紹的是
Mr. Araka's laser mechanism
阿拉卡先生的這個雷射機質
laser assist
雷射輔助
Lei Se entrusted oil treatment method
蕾色托付油理法
In fact, it has two important elements
其實它就有兩個重要的元素
The first is called organic matter
第一個是叫做機質
This mechanism is some small molecular acids
這個機質就是一些小分子酸
It is very easy to generate in this light ion
它非常容易產生在這個輕離子
This light ion can be transferred to
這個輕離子可以轉移到
Let it be charged on this analytical sample
這個分析樣品上讓它帶電
The second important element is lace
第二個重要元素就是蕾色
The role of this lace is
這個蕾色的作用就是
When we mix these analytes with the organic
當我們把這些分析物跟機質混在一起的時候
Because lace has energy
因為蕾色帶有能量
So when Lei Se went to take this sample
所以當蕾色去照這個樣品的時候
It will put the organic light ion
它會把這個機質上的輕離子
let it jump out
讓它跳脫出來
and then separated from the analyte
然後再跟分析物分離
so make it electrified
所以讓它可以帶電
when it is electrified
當它帶電之後
It actually uses the concept of a race
它其實是利用一個賽跑的概念
to measure its size
來測它的大小
Its principle is actually very simple
它的原理其實很簡單
after lace sparks it
在蕾色激發它之後
Different molecules will get the same potential energy
不同的分子它會得到相同的電位能
This potential energy is converted into
這個電位能會被轉化成
It's a race in an electric field, a free one out of five
它在一個電場 五場中一個自由的一個賽跑
Then we know that when the potential energy is converted into kinetic energy
那我們知道說電位能轉換成動能的時候
Because this speed, this V means that speed is inversely proportional to mass
因為這個速度 這個V是代表速度跟質量是成反比
So a fat person has a slower speed, and a thinner person has a faster speed
所以胖的人速度就小 瘦的人速度就大
So when the two of us go for a run
所以當我們兩個人一起去跑的時候
fast thin people run fast
快的 瘦的人跑得快
He arrives first and the fat man arrives later
他先到達 然後胖的人跑得晚一點到達
So take advantage of this different flight time
所以利用這個不同的飛行時間
We can analyze the different quality
我們可以去分析出不同的質量
Then this is a very simple principle of Zhipu
那這就是執普很簡單的一個原理
Then it will be difficult
那接下來困難點來了
Please take this matter seriously
請問大家趁重這件事情
use weight for this matter
用重量這件事情
Why can I tell you the different identities of these three people
為什麼可以告訴你這三個人不同的身份
This same one was made by my daughter for me
這張同一篇是我女兒幫我做的
I told her I'm looking for three different people
我跟她說我要找三個不一樣的人
Then she told me to find these three
然後她就跟我說找這三個
please think about it
請問大家想一想
I just mentioned that QP is weighing
我剛提到 質普是稱重
right
對不對
OK, let's look at the weight
好 那我們從重量來看
The lady in the shirt is the thinnest one
這個護衫太太是最瘦的一個
45 kg casually
隨便講45公斤
Those two people are a little bit fatter
那這兩個人稍微胖一點
55 kg
55公斤
I just weighed the thing
我光由稱重這件事情
can i judge
我可不可以去判斷
His name is Hushan, his name is Mizushima, his name is Triangle
他叫護衫 他叫水島 他叫三角
Everyone thinks no, right?
大家覺得不行對不對
Then please think again
那請大家再想想看
can you think or tell me
有沒有能夠想或告訴我
I can only give you a stick scale
我一樣只能給你棒秤
How you can use stick scales
你如何能夠利用棒秤
separate the two
把這兩個人區分出來
Think again, everyone, the concept of weighing
大家再想一想還是稱重的觀念
anyone figured it out
有沒有人想得到
In fact, the reason is very simple
其實道理很簡單
Everyone's body proportions are different
每個人的身材比例不一樣
For example, Mrs. Mizushima has a super big head
譬如說這個水島太太她頭超級大
that her legs are a little bit
那她的腿有一點
also short
也是短短的
then Mrs. Triangle
然後三角太太
her head is bigger
她的頭更大
But look carefully at her hands and feet
可是你仔細看她的手腳
Actually a little thinner
其實比較細一點
if you look carefully
你仔細看的話
So if I cut them up
所以說如果我把她們分屍完
If it is divided into four limbs and disassembled completely
分成四肢全部拆解的話
The proportion of their body
那她們身材的比例
the weight of her hands her head her feet
她的手 她的頭 她的腳的重量
It's actually different
其實是不一樣的
So if each of you looks very different
所以如果你每一個人長得非常不一樣
I can make this limb very precise
我可以把這個四肢做非常精確的
words of weight
重量的話
Then I can actually learn from this so-called combination
那我其實可以從這個所謂的組合
To judge that this is water pouring
去判斷出這個是水倒
this is a triangle
這個是三角
So you use the concept
所以你利用這個概念
You can actually do protein analysis
你其實可以去做蛋白質的分析
purely by weight
純粹靠重量
Then I will use this concept to explain to you
那我接下來就用這個概念來跟大家解釋
Why weighing can start from weighing
為什麼稱重可以從稱重量
to tell you what this protein is
去告訴你這個蛋白質是什麼
Well, this technique is called protein identification.
那這個技術叫做蛋白質身分鑑定
then we know
那我們知道說
This protein is made up of 20 common amino acid arrangements
這個蛋白質是由20個常見的胺基酸排列組合而成
Each amino acid is different because of its structure
那每一個胺基酸因為它結構不一樣
so its weight is completely different
所以它的重量是完全不一樣的
Then I'm going to measure a protein weight today
那我今天要去測一個蛋白質重量的話
If I measure the whole weight, it will be the same as the problem just now
我如果測整個的重量就跟剛剛的問題是一樣
same weight too much
重量一樣的太多
45 kg is too many people
45公斤的人太多
55 kg is too many people
55公斤的人太多
I can't really tell who's who.
我其實沒有辦法去區分到底誰是誰
But if I cut this protein into pieces
可是我如果把這個蛋白質切成片段
Then this cut is of course a regular cut
那這個切當然是有規律的切
At this time, after the protein is cut into fragments
那這個時候這個蛋白質切成片段之後
because every fragment
因為每一個片段
Because this sequence of every protein and amino acid
因為每一個蛋白質和胺基酸的這個序列
is unique
是獨特的
Everyone's sequence is different
每個人序列都不一樣
so when i cut
所以當我切的時候
cut out fragments of this ecology
切下來的這個生態的片段
Its sequence is also unique
它的序列也是獨特的
That's because each amino acid has a different weight
那因為每一個胺基酸重量都不一樣
So this time I can go and put this weight
所以這個時候我可以去把這個重量
Test this separately
分別去測用這個
side out
側出來
Then if the sequence composition of this protein is different
那如果這個蛋白質的序列組成不一樣
The weight of the fragment it produces
它產生出來的片段的重量
Must be a unique set
一定也是獨特的一套
like a fingerprint
像指紋一樣
everyone is different
每個人都不一樣
So using the concept
所以利用這個概念
I can do the comparison
我可以去做比對
So in this methodology
那所以在這個方法學中
We can start with some enzymes
我們可以先用一些酵素
chop protein into pieces
把蛋白質切成碎片
that in this example
那在這個例子中
It uses an enzyme called Tripsing
是用一個叫Tripsing的酵素
These enzymes must be very specific
這些酵素一定會非常特異
it will recognize
它會辨認
specific amino acids it will cut
特定的胺基酸它才會切
so it encounters this red
所以它遇到這個紅色的
it's just
它就切切切切
after you cut
那你切了以後
Because the order of the proteins is different
因為蛋白質這個排列順序不一樣
So you can think of it as saying
所以你可以把它想像成說
each protein has its own
每一個蛋白質都有它自己
A very unique set of Peptide pieces
非常獨特的一套Peptide的碎片
At this time, I will use the mass spectrometer to weigh
那這個時候我再拿質譜去秤
I'm going to test it
我去測一測
The weight of this fragment
這個碎片的重量
what are they
分別是什麼
So I am at this time
所以我這時候
You can put this Peptide
就可以把這個Peptide
this pile of debris
這一大堆的碎片
To measure mass spectrometry
去測質譜
Then this mass spectrum is a snack
那這個質譜這是一張點心的
That means mass means weight
那這個代表質量就是重量的意思
So this goes from 600 weight to 3000
所以這從600重量到3000
Each bar represents the weight of each segment
每一根就是代表每一段的重量
Even QP can help you measure all the weight
就是質普也可以幫你把這個重量全部測出來
After this quality
那這個有了這個質普之後
I'm going to ask next
接下來我接下來就要去問
In the database we just mentioned
在資料庫之中我們剛剛有提到
DNA produces RNA
DNA產生RNA
So as long as the DNA sequence is determined
所以只要DNA的序列確定
Possibility of producing RNA to produce protein
產生RNA到產生蛋白質的可能性
know all
是全部都知道的
So I have a large database
所以我有一個很大的資料庫
I skip this first
我先跳過這個
I have a large database
我有一個很大的資料庫
in this database
這個資料庫中
has the sequence of each protein
有每一個蛋白質的序列
The sequence of each protein is inside
每一個蛋白質的序列都在裡頭
So my next step is to ask
所以我下一步就要去問
ask the computer
請問電腦
in all your databases
在你所有的資料庫之中
which protein sequence
哪一個蛋白質序列
Most likely to produce the quality just now
最有可能產生剛剛那個質普
so this time
所以這個時候
You need to ask the computer to do the calculation for you
你要叫電腦去幫你做計算
follow your orders
按照你的吩咐
Meet this Lizing in red
遇到紅色的這個Lizing
specific amino acid
就特定的胺基酸
it's just
它就切切切切
it takes every protein
它就把每一個蛋白質
all possible theoretical
所有可能產生理論的質
Calculate it all for you
全部幫你計算出來
So after it calculates 30,000 records
所以它計算之後三萬筆資料
Every data has
每一筆資料都有
Then you go to pen pair
然後你再去做筆對
Which protein is closest to the experimental quality
哪一個的蛋白質最接近這個實驗質
Then it will tell you at this time
那這個時候它就告訴你
I know it's the protein
我知道是這個蛋白質
So just now I omitted one
所以剛剛我省略一張
So in this step three
所以在這個步驟三
is that you have to take this result you got
就是你必須把你得到的這個結果
Send it to the computer database to do pen pairing
送到電腦資料庫裡面去做筆對
You tell him how you're going to cut
你告訴他說你要怎麼去切
Do I have some protein?
那我蛋白質有沒有一些
For example, we just talked about adding a zero acid
譬如說我們剛剛講加上一個零酸
it weighs differently
它重量就不一樣
Was it added or not?
那有沒有加還是沒加
And then it's interesting
然後還有很有趣的是
you have to tell it the database
你要告訴它資料庫
Like before we try first it used to happen
像以前我們先試曾經發生過
a very funny thing
一個非常好笑的事
The director of a certain hospital told us
就是某一個醫院的主任跟我們講說
This is the patient's sample
這個是病人的檢體
How to test is a mouse
怎麼測就是老鼠
It's a mouse
就是老鼠
It was later discovered that
後來才發現那個是
that his sample was contaminated
那個他的樣品被汙染
And there was a very serious thing that happened
那還有曾經發生過一件很嚴重的事
I have a friend
我有一個朋友
he is in a core facility
他是在一個核心設施
Then the detected protein is AIDS protein
然後測出來的蛋白質是愛滋病的蛋白
The HIV virus must be above P3 level
那愛滋病毒是必須要在P3等級以上
can do
才可以做的
then that
然後那個
Then it was a coincidence
然後那時候就是很巧
The Poster that happened to be sent for testing
正好送測的那個一個Postar
he has no concept
他沒有概念
He thought that AIDS came from himself
他以為愛滋病是他自己跑出來的
This time there was no concept of a bitch
這上次沒有位教的觀念
so he is nervous
所以他很緊張
He ran to the hospital for examination
他跑去醫院檢查
His wife also went to check
他太太也去檢查
Will he get AIDS
他會不會得愛滋病
Then of course not
後來當然就不是
The reason that was finally found out was that
那最後真正查到的原因就是
that laboratory is contaminated
那間實驗室被汙染
It's that they take a cell from another lab
就是他們從別的實驗室拿一個細胞
Turns out that cell is infected with HIV
結果那個細胞被愛滋病毒感染
that is an extremely dangerous thing
那這是一件極度危險的事情
Fortunately later
還好後來
It was my friend who detected this.
就是我那個朋友測到這件事情
AIDS detected
測到愛滋病
So that lab was wiped out afterward.
所以後來那間實驗室全部清掉
So Straight Spectrum Ritual A
所以直譜儀式一個
very sensitive method
非常非常靈敏的一個方法
Then we still have a lot of fun experience
那我們現在還有很多很好玩經驗
For example, someone wants to make Taiwan's unique fish species
譬如說有人要做台灣特有的魚種
fish are not genetically present
魚是沒有基因目前
Then you have to find something similar or not as good
那你就要找類似的、不如類的
to do this analysis
來做這個分析
ok , so a method like this
好,那所以這樣一個方法
because every protein
因為每一個蛋白質
the quality of the ecology it produces
它所產生的生態的質量
like a fingerprint
就像指紋一樣
So such a method
所以這樣一個方法
protein identification
叫做蛋白質的身份鑑定
Then with this method
那有了這個方法之後
greatly surpassed our
大大的突破了我們對於
Protein Analysis Challenges and Limitations
蛋白質分析的挑戰跟限制
In the past, you had to analyze a protein
在以前,你要去分析個蛋白質
you have to save it
你必須要把它存化出來
Then do the analysis
然後再去做分析
One protein could take you two years
一個蛋白質可能花你兩年的時間
But now you only need one cell
可是現在你只要一個細胞
You do paper spectrum analysis for two hours
你做紙譜分析兩小時
you get at least a few hundred
你至少得到幾百個
Even the data of thousands of proteins
甚至好幾千個蛋白質的這個資料
can know very quickly
都可以非常快速的知道
it all depends on
那這都有賴於
The continuous improvement of paper notation technology
現在紙譜技術的不斷的精進
and this analysis technology information technology
還有這個分析技術 資訊技術
This refinement of information software
資訊軟體的這個精進
the next question is
那下一個問題是
we have this technology
我們有了這個技術
then can we ask a question
那我們可不可以去問一個問題
How many proteins are there in humans
人類到底有多少個蛋白質組成
Can we, as just mentioned
我們可不可以像剛剛所提到
Human Genetic Project
人類基因的計畫
Genome's plan is the same
基因體的計畫一樣
Find out all the human protein maps
去把人類的蛋白質圖全部找出來
The most crucial question is
那一個最關鍵的問題是
we keep asking
我們一直在問
Actually this is still unanswered
其實這個還是沒有答案
Does each gene produce a corresponding protein?
每一個基因都會產生一個相對應的蛋白嗎
is this the answer
這個答案是嗎
not necessarily
不見得
How much protein does a human have
人類有多少蛋白質組成
have no idea
不知道
There's no way to be 100% sure yet
現在還沒有辦法百分之百確定
Of course the more important question
那當然更重要的問題
If we want to be able to treat diseases
我們如果希望能夠對疾病
Learn more about life functions
對生命功能多一些了解
we want to find
我們想要去找到
Key molecules in these regulation
這些調控的關鍵分子
to help us understand
來幫助我們了解
even go
甚至去
The so-called control of the disease
所謂去調控這個疾病
even suppress it
甚至去抑制它
that's important in this
那在這個重要的
Human Protein is under the project of relative human genome
Human Protein 就是相對人類基因體的計畫之下
There is a very important international organization called
有一個非常重要的國際組織叫做
International Protein Organization abbreviated as HuPo
國際蛋白質組織 簡稱叫做HuPo
Then HuPo in 2012
那HuPo在2012年的時候
They started a huge collaborative project all over the world
他們開始了一個全世界的大型合作計畫
Then they want to be like the Human Genome Project
那他們希望能夠像人類基因體計畫一樣
able to convert every possible protein
能夠把每一個可能產生的蛋白質
find it all
全部都把它找出來
This project was developed by several people at that time
這個計畫那時候是由幾個人
Included in Yongki Pack in Korea
包括在韓國的Yongki Pack
Hankhawk in the United States
在美國的Hankhawk
and Sweden in Europe
還有在歐洲的瑞典
They co-signed such a plan
他們共同簽了這樣一個計畫
The level of this program is very, very many people participating
這個計畫的層面非常非常多人參加
A total of 25 countries are involved in this chromosome
總共有25個國家參與了這個染色體
Chromosome-based Human Proteome Project
以染色體為主的人類蛋白質體計畫
Then why is it called a chromosome
那它為什麼叫染色體
because it is based on chromosomes
是因為它是以染色體為單位
then you can see
那你可以看到
That is, we in Taiwan have chromosome 4
就是我們台灣是4號染色體
One reason for picking number 4
那挑選4號的一個原因
actually in the early days
其實是在早期
There are some scholars in Taiwan
台灣有一些學者
Especially at Yangming University
尤其在陽明大學
when they participated in the Human Genome Project
他們在參加人類基因體計畫的時候
This is dominated by chromosome 4
這個是以4號染色體為主
And the Alpha-Vetal Protein of liver cancer
而且肝癌這個Alpha-Vetal Protein
Molecules of this liver cancer
這個肝癌的分子
on chromosome 4
是在4號染色體上面
Then I am happiest that our mainland is here
那我最高興的是我們大陸在這裡
In fact, they have been suppressing us
其實他們一直在打壓我們
The last agreement we participated in
那最後我們參加的協議書
in the name of Taiwan
是以台灣的名稱
And they agree that we can fly the flag
而且他們同意我們可以放國旗
it's the thing i'm most proud of
這是我最驕傲的事
Then the mainland has also expanded very large in the past few years
然後大陸在這幾年也膨脹得非常的大
that he for... you can see
那他為...你可以看到
He started to choose number 8
他一開始去選8號
Later he picked number 1
後來他挑了1號
In fact, the smaller the... the smaller the number, the more difficult it is
其實越...號碼越小越困難
because more protein
因為蛋白質越多
Do you...know why number 1 was chosen?
大家會...知道為什麼選1號嗎
Because he's gonna do Number 1 and that's it
因為他要做Number 1就這樣
so they do number 1
所以他們做1號
In fact, they also asked us for help.
那其實他們也有找我們幫忙
we choose number 4
我們是選4號
Then you can also see like Japan
那你也可以看到像日本
they choose number 3
他們選3號
then different countries
然後不同的國家
like america
像美國
america is here
美國在這裡
America picks No. 17
美國選17號
Because the number 17 is the gene of the lung cancer
因為17號是那個肺癌的這個基因
Important genes are all on number 17
重要的基因都在17號上
Many important cancer genes are also on the 17th
那很多重要的癌症基因也在17號上
there is another interesting
那還有一個有趣
Iran chooses Y
伊朗選Y
Do you know why?
大家知道為什麼嗎
Because the regenerative medicine in Iran is very powerful
因為伊朗非常很厲害的那個再生醫學
They do a lot of that unlucky
他們做很多那個不運症的
So the secret of the skewed body
所以那個歪染涉體上面的祕密
is what they want to know
是他們希望了解
So each country they go to claim
所以每個國家他們去認領
different chromosomes
這個不同的染涉體
has a reason for it
都有它的一個原因
Well, the purpose actually sounds so simple.
那這個目的其實聽起來很單純
But it is very difficult directly
但是直系面上非常困難
The human genome was drafted in 2004
人類基因體在2004年玩稿完成了
About 20,000 genes
大概2萬個基因
human protein body
人類蛋白體多少
have no idea
不知道
This is a target we are looking for now
這個是我們現在在找的一個目標
that in these two years
那在這一兩年
There has been a lot of importance for this work to emerge
有出現了很多重要的這個工作出現
That first big job is there in
那第一個大的工作是有在
He relied on this Pendi professor in the United States
他憑美國的這個Pendi教授
he himself is a doctor
他本身是一個醫生
A doctor of Indian descent
一個印度裔的一個醫生
Then he uses a very large scale mass spectrometer
那他用非常大規模的質譜
he is rich
他很有錢
He made an adult organization of 17 people
他做了17個人的成人的組織
6 types of hematopoietic cells
6種造血細胞
7 more embryonic tissues
還有7種胚胎組織
because an idea is
因為一個想法是
If there are some proteins that have never been present
如果有一些蛋白質一直都沒有存在
No evidence
沒有證據
Could it be because he showed up very early
會不會是因為他在很早時期出現
then disappeared
後來就消失
So he used massive mass spectrometry
所以他用大規模的質譜技術
to identify proteins
去做蛋白質的鑒定
Then this article in Nature
那這篇在Nature
this is the first
這是第一篇
Articles in Nature
在Nature的文章
In total, they identified 17,000 protins
他們總共鑒定到了17000個Protin
About 84% of all genes
大概在所有基因的84%
Then this article came out at the same time
那這篇文章出來之後就同時期
there is a sebecet
有一個塞白塞的
Also in Nature
同時在Nature
There is a Professor Kusse in Germany
在德國有一個Kusse教授
then they are scary too
那他們也是很恐怖
He probably has a real mass spec
他大概有用實臺的質譜
do it hard do it hard
拼命做 拼命做
Then got more than 18000 Protin
然後得到了18000多個Protin
These two are probably so far
這兩個大概是目前為止
A sketch of the largest so-called human protein body
最大規模所謂人類蛋白質體的一個草圖
this is appearing
這個是出現
But after these two jobs
可是在這兩個工作之後
There has been a lot of controversy
出現了非常多的爭議
The reason is Professor Pendi
那原因是Pendi教授呢
His mass spectrometric identification technique is very imprecise
他的質譜鑑定的技術非常不嚴謹
His statistics are many errors
他的統計上很多的錯誤
So it caused a lot of controversy
所以後來引起非常大的爭論
after this job
在這個工作之後
but i personally think
但是我個人是覺得
Actually this is a beginning
其實這就是一個開始
at the same time in sweden
那同時間在瑞典
There is a crazier project
有一個更瘋狂的一個project
This is a big project funded by the government
這個是政府資助的一個大計畫
They take every human protein
他們把每一個人類的蛋白質
all antibodies
全部做抗體
As long as the antibody is produced
那只要抗體做出來
he organizes all
他把所有的組織
Regardless of normal tissue, all cancer tissues are stained
不管正常組織 癌症組織全部染色
he wants to know
他想要去了解
human protein
人類蛋白質
What is the performance in the whole organ?
在整個器官裡面的表現到底是什麼
It is a very large project
是一個非常大的一個project
Then they also published in Size this year
那他們也在今年發表在Size
Use Tissue
用Tissue
immunostaining
然後用免疫染色法
So this is probably
所以這個大概是
Come to the biggest break in a job
來最大的一個工作的突破
after this
那在這個之後
Many other countries have also emerged
也陸陸續續出現了很多其他國家
to look for the so-called mesin protein
去尋找所謂的mesin protein
let me explain here
這邊我解釋一下
Currently about 15% protein
目前大概還有15%的蛋白質
no evidence
沒有任何的證據
no one knows if they exist
沒有人知道他們存不存在
So everyone's first goal
所以大家的第一個目標
is to make these proteins
就是要把這些蛋白質
Is it possible to find all of them?
是不是全部都能夠找到
then you can see it's funny
那你可以看到這很有趣
strange material
都是很奇怪的材料
that's what i just said
就是我剛剛講的
Because everyone will feel that they have done so much
因為大家會覺得做了那麼多
why can't i see
為什麼看不到
it must be somewhere weird
它一定在奇怪的地方
so you can see
所以你可以看到
From sperm to pulp
從搞完精子到牙髓
human beings
人類什麼什麼
Everyone is looking for this mesin protein
大家都去找這個mesin protein
On a larger scale is
比較大規模的是
166個protein machine
166個mesin protein
Of course we in Taiwan cannot lose
我們台灣當然不能輸人
loser does not lose proof
輸人不輸證
we were in 2012
我們是在2012年的時候
it is through them
正是通過他們
It's not that they agree
其實也不是他們同意
Actually they forced us to say
其實他們強迫我們說
Must be Taiwan
一定台灣
Because we were helping others to analyze
因為我們那時候一直在幫別人分析
then he
然後他就
I think you're so good
我認為說你們這麼厲害
why don't you claim it
為什麼自己不認領
So later we passed the Taiwan Proteosome Society
所以後來我們在台灣蛋白體學會通過
We officially claimed chromosome 4
我們正式認領了四號染色體
Then Taiwan is here
然後台灣在這邊
Then the first goal is to put this chromosome 4
然後第一個目標就是希望把這個四號染色體
able to figure out
能夠弄清楚
I am also very grateful to many schools
我也很謝謝非常多的學校
Including National Taiwan University, Yang Ming, National Health Institute
包括台大、陽明、國衛院
There are also high school, City University, etc.
還有高一、城大等等
long root
長根
Every school raises its own money
每個學校都自己去籌錢
Let's do this project together
來共同做這個計畫
Then one of our arguments is
然後我們的一個論點是
The argument in Taiwan is
在台灣的論點是
We don't want to go fearless in search of these proteins
我們不想要無畏地去尋找這些 protein
We want to be able to target cancer
我們希望能夠有目標針對癌症
Because cancer is a common goal of these schools
因為癌症是這些學校共同的一個目標
So we selected the membrane protein of the cell membrane
所以我們選定了細胞膜的膜蛋白
because i just mentioned
因為我剛剛有提過
That is, 70% of them use membrane proteins as the target of drugs
就是 70% 都是以膜蛋白作為藥物的這個標靶
So in this project
所以在這個project 之中
we found an interesting thing
我們發現一個有趣的事情
membrane protein
因為細胞膜的膜蛋白
It is diligently stuck on the membrane of the cell membrane
它是精進地卡在細胞膜的膜上
On the cell membrane, it's very crisp and watery
細胞膜上面 它非常的酥水性
So in fact, the analysis challenge is very big
所以其實在分析的挑戰上是非常大的
So if the membrane protein of the cell membrane
所以如果做細胞膜的膜蛋白
It's actually a very lonely area
其實是很寂寞的一個領域
Then we did an analysis
那我們就去做了一個分析
we found out that
我們發現到說
what is known so far
在目前已經知道的這些
Missing protein inside
Mising protein裡面
about a third
大概有三分之一
all membrane proteins
全部是細胞膜的膜蛋白
So we decided to say
所以我們就決定說
We start with the cell membrane
我們從細胞膜著手
So this is the latest issue that came out
所以在這是最近出來的一期
We combined my lab
我們結合了我實驗室
And Mr. Song Definition
還有宋定義老師
And Teacher Yang Panshi
還有楊潘石老師
Principal Yang Panshi
楊潘石校長
And Alex's professor in the United States
還有在美國的Alex的教授
Together we go to find these membrane proteins
我們共同去尋找這些膜蛋白
our thoughts
我們的想法
Our hypothesis is
我們的假說是
If membrane proteins are important
如果膜蛋白是重要
Well, let me pick a cancer first.
那我其實先挑一個癌症先來看
So we analyzed twenty pairs of lung cancer tissues
所以我們分析了二十對的肺癌組織
Cells from eleven types of lung cancer were analyzed
分析了十一種肺癌的細胞
Then we found
然後我們發現到
Actually we should be
其實我們應該是
The most in this issue
這一期裡面最多的
There are 178
有178個
Mission protein
Mission protein
Then you can see these 178 Mission proteins
然後你可以看到這些178個Mission protein
distributed on different chromosomes
分佈在各個不同的染色體
Nine of them are on chromosome 4
其中有9個是在4號染色體
We found that in fact
我們發現到其實在這裡面
often have a lot of protection
常有很多的保障
Let's say there are 9 new GPCRs
譬如說有9個新的GPCR
This is currently the most important drug target
這個是目前最重要的藥物的標靶
In fact we identified that it exists
事實上我們鑑定到它是存在的
We also verify that it exists
我們也驗證它的存在
but what is its function
可是它的功能是什麼呢
we welcome the people behind
我們很歡迎後面的人
able to continue to work it out
能夠繼續把它研究出來
the most important is
最重要的是
these are so called jigsaw puzzles
這些是所謂的拼圖
These are the so-called analyzes
這些是所謂的分析
But what kind of help does it have for medicine?
可是對於醫學到底有什麼樣的幫助呢
Can we use proteomics
我們可不可以用蛋白質體學
Come help us find new targets for cancer detection
來幫助我們去尋找新的癌症檢測的標靶
It's a big goal for many
這是一個很多人的大目標
Let's take an example
我們舉例子來講
In this cancer is still a
在這個癌症目前還是一個
A disease with the highest fatality rate
致死率最高的一個疾病
then if you go to see
那如果你去看
You see the top three lung cancer liver cancer
你看前三名肺癌肝癌
both men and women are the same
不管男女都是一樣
Lung cancer is now number one
肺癌現在都是第一名
Then liver cancer came in second
然後肝癌在第二名
That rectal cancer has been on the rise
那直腸癌一直在往上升
third place
第三名
In addition to the so-called detection molecules for liver cancer
除了肝癌有所謂檢測的分子之外
And that detector molecule it's not very good
而且那個檢測分子它不是很好
There are no molecular tests for lung cancer and colorectal cancer
肺癌、大腸癌沒有任何的分子檢測
It all depends on the diameter of the large intestine
完全是要靠大腸徑
or you go to take a picture
或者是你去照
You go to analyze this image
你去照這個影像分析
to be able to see
才能夠看得出來
None of the molecular tests
沒有任何一個分子檢測
So if in summary
所以如果總結來講
currently in clinical use
目前在臨床上使用
These cancer marker proteins are very, very limited
這些癌症標記蛋白種類非常非常有限
that's all
就只有這些
Many diseases are not tested
很多病是沒有檢測的
so we keep asking
所以我們一直在問說
Can we go find new marker proteins
我們可不可以去尋找新的標記蛋白
So what is a marker protein?
那什麼叫標記蛋白呢
it means
它意思就是
when you are sick or when you have a symptom
當你生病或當你有一個症狀
not necessarily sick
不見得是生病
For example, you can be high
譬如說你高性也可以
when a particular symptom
就是某一個特別的症狀的時候
If there is a large increase in protein under this symptom
如果這個症狀下有一個大量增加的蛋白
And this large increase is due to the disease
而且這個大量增加是因為這個疾病造成的
or its specific
或者是它特有的
Then we call this protein a marker protein
那我們就把這個蛋白質叫做標記蛋白
Then this marker protein is very, very important
那這個標記蛋白就非常非常重要
you can help the doctor
你可以去幫助醫生
For example, some proteins can tell you
譬如說有些蛋白可以告訴你
This of the prevention of cardiovascular disease
心血管疾病的預防的這個
marker protein
的標記蛋白
or like a cancer target
或者是像癌症標靶
you can test first
你可以先去測
Does EGFR show
EGFR有沒有表現
Is there a mutation
有沒有突變
Only you can eat this shit
有你才能夠去吃這個飆
Soaring soaring will be effective
飆飆飆才會有效
So if these marker proteins
那所以如果有這些標記蛋白
Then we can actually do something like this
那我們事實上可以像這樣
Can there be more diseases?
是不是能有更多的病
be detected earlier
能夠早一點被檢測出來
especially many diseases
那尤其有很多病
still rely on this
還是要靠這個
It's the doctor's judgment
就是醫生的判斷
without any molecular detection or even imaging methods
沒有任何分子檢測或甚至影像方法
Are there any successful examples?
那有沒有成功的例子
I tell you there are
我告訴各位有
This OVA1 is a software for
這個OVA1是一個針對軟體
A kit that loves detection
超愛檢測的一個kit
is the world's first proteomics
是全世界第一個由蛋白質體學
Developed cancer detection reagents
開發出來的癌症檢測試劑
The earliest prototypes were made in the United States
那最早的原型是由在美國
This Daniel Chien professor at John Hopkins
John Hopkins的這個Daniel Chien教授
what they developed
他們所研發出來的
Then this research and development in 2009
那這個研發在2009年的時候
They were later transferred to a company
他們後來計轉給一家公司
Then this 2009 officially passed the FDA certification
然後這個2009年正式通過FDA的認證
he can get tested
他可以去做檢測
Then he targets this malignant tumor
那他針對這個惡性腫瘤
The detection rate of malignant ovarian tumors is as high as 96%.
就是惡性卵巢瘤的檢測率高達96%
Then his normal person is
那他的正常人就是
He has a 95% correct rate without problems
沒有問題的他的正確率也高達95%
so is a very correct
所以是一個非常正確
It is a reagent with high accuracy
就是準確度很高的一個試劑
In the traditional detection method of ovarian cancer
那在傳統卵巢癌的檢測方法上
In fact, everyone is currently using the CA125
其實目前大家在用就是CA125
i just mentioned
我剛剛已經提過
But this Mark is in many, many diseases
可是這個Mark是在很多很多病裡面
will increase, not necessarily ovarian cancer
都會增加不見得是卵巢癌
of course
那當然
then you can go for an ultrasound
那你可以去做超音波
But this requires manual judgment
但是這個就非常需要人工判斷
And when it's sonified
而且當它超音波照到的時候
Actually, it's already a big piece.
其實已經是一塊 很大一塊了
Unable to do this early detection
無法做早期的這個檢測
So in this Professor Daniel Chuen
所以在這個Daniel Chuen教授
They just want to be able to use
他們就是希望能夠用
proteomic methods
蛋白質體學的方法
to find new detections
去找到新的檢測
Then this method is actually
那它這個方法其實是
One of the simplest methods in proteomics
蛋白質體學裡面最簡單的一個方法
They took the patient
他們就把這個病人
Take the blood of healthy testers for testing
跟健康測試者的血液拿去測
Fat test stocks
測脂股
So this is a fat stock chart
所以這個是一張脂股圖
Then every time you see one, it means
那你每看到一根就代表
Oh this is so-and-so protein
喔這是某某某蛋白質
Then it is more concentrated
然後它濃度越高
the higher its signal
它的訊號就越高
Then it is for convenience to analyze
那它為了方便去分析
it puts this high and low
它把這個高高低低
transform like this image
轉變成像這個影像一樣
The darker the color, the higher the concentration
顏色越深就代表濃度越高
Well then it uses this principle
好那它就利用這個原理
To analyze patients with soft bank cancer
去分析了軟鈔癌的病人
patient with health tester
跟健康測試者的病人
Then everyone can digest for 10 seconds
那大家可以先消化10秒鐘
Anyone see anything different?
有人看到哪裡不一樣了嗎
It's not easy to see
其實很不容易看
actually it's pretty awesome
其實它很厲害
if i see this result
要是我看到這個結果
I feel bad
我就覺得結果不好
look carefully
大家仔細看
This one over here
這邊這一條
here is a protein
這邊是一個蛋白質
is this straightening
是這個 straightening
Then the other one is called
然後另外這個是叫
Aolipo suggests A1
Apolypo protein A1
if you look carefully
如果你很仔細看
this place this one
這個地方這一條
Projector is a bit unclear
投影劑有點不清楚
I use to talk
我用講的
just in
就是在
The concentration is decreased when the patient
病人的時候這個濃度是下降
Then there is actually
然後這邊事實上是有
This concentration is slightly higher
這個濃度是稍微高一點
just darker
就是比較黑
you can't see it now
你現在投影劑看不到
So in this example
所以在這個例子之中
They found that three proteins
他們發現有三個蛋白質
Patients with soft-nest cancer followed healthy testers
在軟巢癌的病人跟在健康測試者的
Expressed concentration is not the same
表現量濃度是不一樣的
So then put this
所以後來就把這個
they have another article
他們還有另外一篇文章
How many articles are there in total
兩篇加起來總共有幾篇
Then they take this seven proteins
然後他們就把這個七個蛋白質
Credit to Virvanian
記轉給Virvanian
This company
這家公司
Then this company has these seven proteins
那這家公司就有這七個蛋白質
to do it on a large scale
去做了很大規模
It's a clinical test in several medical centers
就是好幾個醫學中心的臨床測試
Finally, a combination of these five proteins was found
最後發現這五個蛋白質的組合
You can do this test of OVA1
可以去做OVA1的這個測試
OK, so after this test is done,
好 所以這個測試做了以後
it can target is
它可以針對就是
The one before and after the period
那個跟年期前跟年期以後
it has a different score
它有不同的一個分數
it will tell you
它會告訴你說
Your current tumor
你現在的這個腫瘤
Is it a malignant or benign tumor
到底是惡性的還是良性腫瘤
If a benign tumor
那如果良性腫瘤
Back to obstetrics of course
當然就回到副產科
Malignant tumors need to be treated
惡性腫瘤就要去做處理
After the reagent comes out
那這個試劑出來之後
You can see it in 2012 when
你可以看到它在2012年的時候
Has reached as high as 10,000 to 20,000 reagents
已經高達有一、兩萬個試劑
used in the US
在美國使用
So this is a successful
所以這個是一個成功的
This result translated from proteomics
從蛋白質體學轉譯出來的這個成果
But here I want to tell you
但是這邊我要跟各位講
In fact, Professor Daniel Chuen
其實Daniel Chuen教授
The one he passed FDA in this kit
他在這個kit通過FDA認證的那個
when he gave his first speech
他第一次演講的時候
He will tell you as soon as he goes up
他一上去就跟你說
just tell everyone
就跟大家說
Nine years ago I told you it would work
九年前我就告訴你們會成功
In fact, no one believed that he would succeed.
其實大家都不相信他會成功
The development took nine years
這個發展花了九年的時間
Therefore, when the biotechnology industry has many
所以生技產業很多的時候
is a long
是一個漫長的
because you have to do a lot
因為你要做很多很多的
a generation of four seasons
一個四季的產生
From the seven proteins how
從七個 protein 怎麼
in the beginning from a pile of blood
一開始從一堆血
how to pick seven
怎麼挑到七個
How to reduce seven to five
七個怎麼縮減到五個
how to do five
五個要怎麼去做
then this
然後這個
It depends on how high or low the concentration is
就濃度要多高多低
Where do you cut to do testing
你砍在哪裡才能做檢測
Then you want every doctor to cooperate with you
然後你要每個醫生都要跟你配合
and multiple medical centers
而且還要多個醫學中心
do it together
共同來做
So this is actually a
所以這其實是一個
very long process
非常漫長的一個過程
So we also want
所以我們也希望
Please give the hospital more time
大家給中醫院多一點時間
We are working hard on research
我們很努力的在做研究
Another very important job
另外一個很重要的工作
was published last year
是在去年發表的
just doing a test
剛剛是在做檢測
National Institutes of Health
美國國家衛生研究院
Is doing clinical proteomics
是在做臨床蛋白質體
teacher in school
學裡面的教教者
That's a scary one too
那這也是一個很恐怖的
They are jointly conducted by five research units
他們是五個研究單位共同來做
including John Hopkins
包括John Hopkins
Included in Frey Hutchinson
包括在Frey Hutchinson
a well-known research unit
一個很有名的研究單位
an alliance to do together
共同來做的一個聯盟
they want to ask
他們就想問說
Is it possible to learn from the gene body and the protein body
可不可以從基因體跟蛋白體
combine the two
兩個把它結合
Come tell us common sense cancer
來告訴我們大常識長癌
Can it be divided into different types
到底可不可以分成不同的型
that's actually very important
那這其實很重要
Because common sense grows in the United States
因為大常識長在美國超大
Then let's look at the genome
那我們先看基因體
This picture is a bit complicated
這張圖有點複雜
but let me explain
但是請讓我跟大家解釋一下
I only talk about the genetic part
我只講基因的部分
in genetic analysis
在基因的分析裡面
they are very large
他們非常大規模
Spend a lot of money doing genome analysis
花了很多錢去做基因體的分析
100 people
100個人
You can see that the genes are divided into three large
你可以看到基因分成三大型
Then this black, yellow and blue
那這個黑色、黃色跟藍色
In fact, it is divided into three major
它事實上總共分了三大型
that big one is
那一大型就是
I don't want to talk
我不要講好
this may be too complicated
這大家可能太複雜
three different types
就是三種不同的型態
But if you look at protein
可是如果你去看蛋白質
This one is protein
上面這個是蛋白質
it can be clearly
它可以很明確地
Divided into five major
分成五大型
Then they later discovered that the five large
那他們後來發現這五大型
Actually there is a district
其實有一區
There is an area of ​​this area of ​​C
有一區這個C的這一區
It's so fine, I can't see it
是精的看不太出來的
It is interesting that the type of C
那很有趣的是C的這一型
adipose bowel cancer in the second stage
是比較發生在第二期的大腸脂腸癌
And what?
而且呢
It's more like that tumor stem cell
它比較像那個腫瘤幹細胞
because many people think
因為很多人認為說
Stem cells are responsible for cancer recurrence
幹細胞是產生癌症復發的
one of the most culprits
一個最元兇的一個分子
So they found out that
所以他們發現說
C's as long as there are C's this group of people
C的只要有C的這一群人
all in the second issue
都在第二期
Then much like the nature of stem cells
然後很像幹細胞的性質
So they judge from this side that
所以他們從這邊判斷說
If it looks like C from this organization
如果從這個組織看起來是C的
that may require special attention
那可能要特別注意
Because of it the patient's recovery
因為它這個病人的癒後
may not be added
可能是不加的
The doctor should do more aggressive treatment
醫生就要做比較積極的這個治療
so from here
所以從這個地方
you can understand that
你可以了解就是
Gene sees three types
基因看到了三型
But the protein sees the five types
可是蛋白質看到了五型
So you can see in this
所以你可以看到在這個
each row
每一排
Each row represents a protein
這每一排是代表一個蛋白質
every one
每一一
what is it called
這叫什麼
One is all right, each one represents a patient
一條好了 每一條代表一個病人
so you can see
所以你可以看到
Then the red, red, blue and blue represent
那這個紅紅藍藍就代表說
May be higher or lower in concentration
可能在濃度的表現上比較高或比較低
The redder the higher the concentration
越紅的就是濃度越高
The bluer is the lower the concentration
越藍就是濃度越低
So you use this analysis of the protein
所以你利用蛋白質的這個分析
You can in fact very clearly classify all patients
你可以事實上可以很清楚的把所有的病人
Divided into five major
分成五大型
Then this is for future doctors after surgery
那這個就對於將來醫生手術之後
He can go to assist the doctor to judge
他可以去協助醫生去判斷
Should these people be treated more aggressively afterward?
這些人到底他之後的治療要不要更積極
or general treatment
還是用一般的治療都可以
that's a lot of work
那這是一個很大的工作
Then we also want to say
那我們自己也在想說
Can we develop some new methods
我們可不可以發展一些新的方法
Especially I just mentioned lung cancer in Taiwan and lung cancer in foreign countries
尤其我剛剛有提到像台灣的肺癌跟國外的肺癌
Lung cancer in Asia is very different from lung cancer in the West
亞洲的肺癌跟西方的肺癌非常不一樣
But if you go to the hospital
可是如果你去醫院看
All treatments are imported from the West
所有的治療方針都是從西方過來的
so I've always wanted to be able to target
所以我一直很希望能夠去針對
We are unique to these problems to do this
我們特有的這些問題來做這件事
The other one is in this methodology
那另外一個是在這個方法學上
Personalized medicine
我自己認為說個人化醫療
Definitely the era of the future
鐵定是未來的時代
So if you want to do personalized medicine
所以呢如果要做針對個人化的醫療
Must have personal testing tools
一定要有個人化檢測的工具
in order to do the corresponding response
才能去做相對的這個因應
So what we've been developing is
所以我們一直在發展的是
Strategies for Personalized Proteome Analysis
個人化蛋白質體分析的策略
This is my personal research interest
這個是我個人的一個研究興趣
analysis of the patient
那面對病人的分析
Actually you have a lot of challenges
其實你有非常多的挑戰
because you have to do enough patients
因為你必須要做足夠多的病人
in order to conclude
才能過去做歸納
So you are above the method
所以你在方法上面
you wish it was as simple as possible
你希望越簡單越好
Usually the doctor must take most of the specimens
通常那個醫生一定把大部分的檢體
take it for medical treatment
都拿去做病理
Then only a small part will be given to you
那只有少部分剩下來才會給你
Especially the earlier patients
那尤其越早期的病人
Your samples are getting less and less
你的samples越來越少
So microanalysis is also an important thing
所以微量的分析也是一個重要的事情
then of course you wish
然後當然你希望
can do this analysis very quickly
能夠很快速來做這個分析
In addition, we think that
那此外我們認為說
In cancer tissue is actually an analysis
在癌症組織其實是一個分析
cancer marker protein
癌症標記蛋白
a good material
一個很好的材料
The reason is already large and has been found
原因是已經大已經發現
This is the blood vessel
這個是代表血管
Usually the tumor is near the blood vessel
通常腫瘤是在血管這個附近
on this tumor
在這個腫瘤上面
Marker protein on this tumor
這個腫瘤上面的標記蛋白
Its concentration is usually the highest
它的濃度通常是最高的
It is very likely that these proteins
這些蛋白質非常有可能
in many ways
會透過很多的方式
Including through the cancer cells will come out
包括透過癌症細胞會跑出來
So now many people are testing their blood
所以現在很多人在測血液之中
circulating tumor cells
循環的這些腫瘤細胞
In addition, this cell grinding protein
此外這個細胞磨磨蛋白
it has a mechanism
它有一個機制
It's going to come out with the front end cut off
它的前端被切掉以後就會跑出來
the last one is
最後一個是
There are many scissor-like enzymes on the tumor
在腫瘤上面有很多像剪刀一樣的酵素
it cuts these proteins
它會把這些蛋白質剪下來
So through these three mechanisms
所以透過這三個機制
We thought if I could analyze
我們認為如果我能夠去分析
protein on tumor
腫瘤上的蛋白
then go to the blood
然後再去血液中
I can do so-called non-invasive tests
我就可以去做所謂非侵入性的檢驗
I'm going to do a blood test
我去血液中做檢測
The most important thing is when you are in the concentration above
最重要的是當你在上面的濃度
The difference in concentration after running down is 1500
跟在跑下來濃度差到1500
So in terms of analysis
所以就分析來講
In fact, it is relatively easy to analyze this high concentration.
其實分析這個高濃度是比較容易做的
this is what we think
這是我們的想法
we were a few years ago
我們在幾年前
first developed a
先開發了一個
Analytical methods for personalization
針對個人化的分析方法
This example is with
這個例子是跟
Dr. Chen Jingxun at Changgan Hospital
在長根醫院的陳靜勳 陳醫師
he is a very good surgeon
他是一個非常優秀的外科醫生
If you go to see the current colorectal cancer
如果你去看目前大腸子腸癌
All are invasive analysis methods
全部都是侵入式的分析方法
In fact, there is no such method for molecular detection
其實沒有任何分子檢測的這個方法
So we analyzed
所以我們就分析了
we developed a
我們就發展了一個
Very easy way in three steps
三步步驟的很簡單的方法
For each patient, we analyze his cancer tissue
每一個病人我們就去分析他癌症組織
normal tissue near the cancer
跟癌症附近的正常組織
Because we think people are very different from each other
因為我們認為人跟人之間差異很大
Like the Nature article I just mentioned
像我剛剛提到那篇Nature的文章
US NCI they only analyze cancer tissue
美國NCI他們只分析癌症的組織
he didn't actually go to see
他其實沒有去看
Differences between normal tissue and cancer
正常組織跟癌症的差異
We think people are too different
我們認為人跟人差異太大
You are better than people
你要比人跟人之間其實
not too many variables
沒有太大的變數很多
So what we hope to do is to compare ourselves
所以我們希望做的是自己比自己
It's your own cancer compared to your own normal tissue
就是你自己的癌症比上自己的正常組織
So everyone just compares themselves
所以每個人就只跟自己比
Then we went to analyze this
然後我們去分析了這個
we just kept mentioning
我們剛剛一直在提到
membrane protein
這個細胞膜的膜蛋白
Then we analyzed a total of 28
那我們總共分析了28位
patients at different times
不同時期的病人
that in the process
那在這個過程之中
In fact, information is a very, very big challenge
其實資訊是一個非常非常大的挑戰
Our fatty skin produces
我們這個脂肤產生
It could be 100,000 graphs
它可能是10萬張圖譜
You can't do the comparison manually
你不可能用人工去做比對
That's about 7 or 8 years or 4 years in the past
那在這過去大概將近7、8年4年來
we are very very grateful
我們非常非常感謝
at the Central Plains Institute Information Office
在中原院資訊所的
Teacher Song Deyi and Teacher Xu Wennian
宋定義老師和許文年老師
We co-developed a lot of software
我們共同開發了非常多的軟體
without their assistance
那沒有他們的這些協助
we have no way
我們完全沒有辦法
that data is huge
那數據非常龐大
then advertise
然後也廣告一下
That teacher Xu Wennian is the inventor of the natural input method
那個許文年老師是自然輸入法的發明人
I advertise for him
我幫他廣告
Please use it more
請大家多多去使用
But into the law
但是入法
But he said he didn't make a dime
不過他說他一毛錢都沒有賺到
let everyone use
讓大家使用
ok so in the process
好 那所以在這過程中
In this new method
在這新的方法中
The first thing we ask is
我們第一個要問的是
Can we measure
我們可不可以測得到
already in clinical use
臨床上已經在用的
The molecule CEA
CEA這個分子
because it means that your method is feasible
因為這代表你的方法是可行的
that's good of course
那當然很好
we can easily detect
我們很容易測到
then you can see
那你可以看到
everyone
每一個人
If you compare cancer tissue to normal tissue
如果你去比較癌症組織跟正常組織
You go and see this increase in protein concentration
你去看看這個蛋白質濃度增加
nearly three times
將近三倍
that another patient
那另外一個病人
about three times
大概也都是三倍
several times
幾倍
ok so say
好 所以都表示
Our strategy idea should be OK
我們的策略的想法應該是OK的
You can easily see it from the organization
你測組織上是很容易看得出來
That
那
Then here you can see
然後這邊你可以看到
why personalize
為什麼要做個人化
The red dot represents
這個紅色點點就代表
Concentrations in cancer are increased
濃度在癌症的是增加
Click on the big rep for this protein
點閱大代表這個蛋白質
The more the concentration increases
濃度增加的越多
ok so you can see
好 所以你可以看到
In addition to CEA
除了CEA之外
In fact, there is a lot of protein
其實還有非常多的蛋白質
is worth doing
是值得去做的
Good but it was a pity for the times
好 但是那個時代很遺憾
A lot of people
很多人
If you want to verify the antibody is not acceptable
如果你要去驗證抗體是不行的
Then I think our lab will go back now
那我想我們實驗室現在會再回頭
Let's do it with branch spectrum
來用支譜來做這件事
Then if you use the traditional method
那如果你用傳統的方法
The previous method is that the sensitivity is not good enough
以前的人的方法就是靈敏度不夠好
So he has to put all the simplified
所以他必須把所有的簡體
mix it all up
都把它混在一起
Then become a group of normal, a group of cancer
然後變成一群正常 一群癌症
but sometimes
可是有的時候
For example, look at this example
譬如說你看這個例子
If I look at his average
我如果去看他的平均值
This concentration looks high
這個濃度看起來很高
You thought it was a good test to do
你以為這是一個好的可以做檢測
Actually wrong
事實上錯
It is because A is actually the two
是因為A其實這兩個
There are two strange patients with particularly high concentrations
有兩個奇怪的病人濃度特別高
So on average, his concentration is very high
所以平均以後他濃度特別高
In fact, just because two people increase
事實上只是因為兩個人增加
that a good test
那一個好的檢測
You want most people to be able to increase
你希望大部分的人都能夠增加
are increased
都是增加的
You can single out most of the patients
你才能夠把大部分的病人都挑出來
so from here
所以從這個地方
I want to remind everyone that
我要提醒大家就是
Design of Experiments in Doing Research
在做研究的實驗的設計
Special consideration must be given to individual differences
要特別考慮到人跟人之間差異
actually very big
其實是非常的大
Here we are very grateful to Chang Root University
那在這邊我們很謝謝長根大學
Professor Dechang Zhan and Professor Yu Zhaosong
的詹德昌教授和余兆松教授
They did the back for us
他們替我們去做了後面
Method of staining with tissue
用組織染色的方法
Go find a Stone II protein
去找到一個Stone II的蛋白質
Then you can distinguish
然後可以去區分
Normal Washed Meat and Colorectal Cancer Tissue
正常洗肉和大腸癌的組織
Of these 400 patients
在這個400個病人中
So say this protein
所以表示說這個蛋白質
yes can do aftercare
是可以去做癒後
can go and see how it is
可以去看看它狀況是怎麼樣
Then we also look at its five-year survival rate
然後我們也去看它五年存活率
we found that
我們發現說
If the protein concentration is relatively high
這個蛋白質如果濃度比較高的
This axis is represented by
這個軸是代表
It's the chance of being alive within five years
就是五年內人還活著的機率
this represents time
這是代表時間
You can see that the survival rate is relatively low
你可以看到這個存活率是比較低的
If the protein concentration is lower
如果這個蛋白質濃度比較低一點的
higher survival rate
存活率就比較高
So representing the concentration of this protein
所以代表這個蛋白質的濃度
With this patient with colorectal fatty bowel cancer
跟這個大腸脂腸癌病人
Can you live a good life?
是不是能夠好好的活下去
or we say later
或者我們說癒後
is an indicator that may be used
是一個可能可以用的一個指標
Then you can see that the five-year survival rate is high
那你可以看到五年的存活率在高的
Only 42% of those with high performance
表現量高的只有42%
If the patient's concentration is relatively low
那如果這個病人濃度比較低的
His survival rate is relatively high, 75%
他存活率是比較高 有75%
The last thing we want to ask is
那最後面我們要問的是
Can I do a test?
可不可以做檢測
then you can see we don't do a lot
那你可以看到我們沒有做很多
75 patients
75個病人
then you can see in the blood
那你可以看到在血液之中
this protein exists
這個蛋白質是存在的
Then if you use the CEA used in this hospital
那如果用這個醫院裡面用的CEA
he's really bad
他真的很不行
early diagnosis
早期的診斷
Only 14% of him can detect it
他只有14%測得出來
But if you add stone2
可是如果加上stone2
If stone2 can be used to measure 69%
如果用stone2可以有69%測得出來
Then if you put two pits
那如果你把兩個坑敗
76% can be seen
76%是可以看得出來
So from here I think I'll tell you
所以從這個地方我想就告訴你
In fact, proteomics is a
其實蛋白質體學是一個
help you find possible
幫你找到可能的
A new method for the identification of marker proteins
鑑定的標記蛋白的一個新的一個方法
Of course there are still many problems
那當然還有很多的問題
For example, we just talked about protein concentration
譬如說剛剛講的是蛋白質濃度
protein modification
可是蛋白質的修飾
include sugar plan
包括糖計畫
he regulates the immune system
他去調控免疫
into the protein
到蛋白質裡面的
Acidifying it will regulate the transmission of messages
靈酸化它會去調控訊息傳遞
These are also very important
那這些也是一個非常重要
to regulate the process of message transmission
去調控訊息傳遞的一個過程
I just said that
那這我剛剛講過了
So we also hope to have a good way
所以我們也希望能夠有好的方法
able to take the whole system
能夠去把這整個系統
able to identify
能夠鑑定出來
then we wish to say
那我們希望說
able in the process
能夠在這過程之中
to find a molecule in the middle of the messaging
去找到一個訊息傳遞中間的分子
to develop something like this
去發展出像這樣子
A strategy to block a target of protein acidification
阻斷蛋白質靈酸化的一個標靶的策略
that's in this part
那在這個部分
We also developed a new method
我們也發展了一個新的一個方法
When we say an acidification or a modification
當我們說一個靈酸化或一個修飾的時候
if chemical reaction
如果是化學反應
it is known
我們都知道
We have to go after the chemical reaction
我們必須要去算化學反應之後
what dose it responds to
它的反應的劑量是多少
Let's say 400 percent is complete
譬如說百分之四百都完成了
Still 30% deep dance
還是有30%的深層舞
But in the field of spiritual acidification
可是在靈酸化這個領域
we discover
我們發現
It seems that everyone doesn't care much about this matter.
好像大家都不太去在乎這件事情
just ask
大家就只問
Is this protein acidified?
這個蛋白質有沒有靈酸化
it doubles five times
它增加兩倍 五倍
Naling is acidified to the end
那靈酸化到底
Thirty-three percent
到底是百分之三十三
one third acidified
三分之一被凌酸化
Or are they all acidified?
還是全部都被凌酸化
In fact, no one has asked this question
其實大家沒有去問這個問題
so we last year
所以我們在去年
No this year
不對 今年
We published a new method
我們發表了一個新的方法
We measure protein phosphorylation
我們去測蛋白質凌酸化
drug resistance in lung cancer
到底對於肺癌的抗藥性
Is it possible to do something new for this answer
可不可以做一些新的這個答案
So we went to analyze
所以我們就去分析了
This drug-resistant lung cancer
這個一個抗藥性的這個肺癌
sorry
對不起
According to the cells that are sensitive to this Aretha
據針對這個艾瑞莎有敏感度的細胞
and lung cancer cells resistant to it
和對它產生抗藥性的肺癌細胞
we want to ask
我們想要去問
What molecules can produce drug resistance
什麼分子能夠產生抗藥性
then we will analyze
那我們就去分析了
use this method to analyze
用這個方法去分析了
For the law and CK2
針對依倔法跟CK2
These two very important ones
這兩個非常重要的一個機梅
well they will acidify
好 他們會產生凌酸化
then we should say accident
那我們應該說意外
this is a bit
這個是有點
surprised find says
驚訝的發現說
In this network of protein actions
在這個蛋白質的作用的網路之中
We found that these large changes
我們發現這些變化比較大的
The red moon represents the time of drug resistance
月紅色就是代表在抗藥性的時候
Its concentration increases
它的濃度越增加的
We found these molecules
我們發現這些分子
Its change is not due to the concentration of the protein
它的變化並不是來自於蛋白質的濃度
It comes from an increase in protein zero acidification
它來自的是蛋白質零酸化的增加
That is to say, in this control
也就是說在這個調控之中
We found zero acidification changes
我們發現零酸化的變化
may be more important than changes in concentration
可能是比濃度的改變來得更重要的
I can't show a data today
我今天沒有辦法秀一個data
But one of the molecules
但是其中有一個分子
With the assistance of Yang Panchi and Principal Yang
經過楊潘池、楊校長的協助
We found that after kicking out that molecule
我們發現說把那個分子踢除之後
drug resistant cells
可以讓抗藥性的細胞
Cells Reverted to Sensitivity
回復到敏感度的細胞
So I guess it's also proteomics
所以我想這也是蛋白質體學
able to tell us
能夠來告訴我們
Mechanisms of the disease, mechanisms of drug resistance
這個疾病的機制、抗藥性的機制
what exactly is it
到底是什麼
and then give it to biologists or chemists
然後再提供給生物學家或化學家
to design a new therapy
去設計新的這個療法
that last
那最後
I'll talk about it in two or three minutes later.
後面我花個兩三分鐘講一下
In the above, these are more personal research.
在前面這些都是比較個人的這個研究
In fact, everyone in Taiwan has realized that
那其實在台灣大家已經意識到說
It is very important to deal with cancer and disease
對付癌症、對付疾病是一件非常重要的事情
So there are some big medical universities in Academia Sinica
所以在中研院還有一些大的醫學大學
With the efforts of the medical center
跟醫學中心的努力之下
In fact, there are several very important projects
其實有幾個非常重要的計畫
in progress
正在進行之中
First of all, the first one is the Taiwan Human Biology Database
那首先第一個是台灣人體生物資料庫
I don't know if you guys have heard of this
我不知道各位有沒有聽過這個
Is there? There are many taxis
有嗎?計程車上面很多
did you notice
大家有沒有注意到
I think it's a big project that I really admire
我覺得這是我非常佩服的一個重大計畫
This project actually started from Academia Sinica
這個計畫其實是從中研院開始
to lead to the idea of ​​blood
去引以血這樣一個想法
The idea is to say
那這個想法就是覺得說
If we are going to get to know Taiwanese well
如果我們要去好好了解台灣人
generation of disease
疾病的生成
Then should we take the samples of the Taiwanese first?
那我們是不是應該先把台灣人的檢體
Whether it is a patient or a sample from the community
不管是病人或社群民眾的檢體
collect first
先蒐集起來
and after collecting
然後蒐集起來之後
Through our long-term follow-up
我們透過長期的追蹤
to understand their clinical development
去了解他們的臨床的發展
and their living habits
還有他們生活習慣
health blah blah
健康等等等等
Then put these data
然後把這些資料
put these data
把這些資料
biochemical reaction with him
跟他生化的反應
make a link
做一個連結
to find out the cause of the disease
來找出治病的這個原因
because it involves
因為這是牽涉到
very very large quantity
非常非常大的數量
According to my personal knowledge
據我個人出錢的了解
They are actually legislating
他們其實在立法上面
made a lot of effort
做了很多的努力
then go talk to the legislature
然後去跟立法院談
talk to the government
跟政府談
It was finally passed in 2012
最後才終於在2012年的通過
The plan is actually
這個計畫其實是
very ambitious plan
非常有企圖心的一個計畫
currently run by
目前是由
Liu Fudong, director of the House Voice Institute
眾議院聲音所劉浮東所長
And the CEO Shen Zhiyang
還有這個執行長沈志揚
Then the main reason is
然後主要的原因是
hope to understand
希望能夠了解
Common Slow Disappearance
常見的慢消
A relationship between STD genes and the environment
性病的基因跟環境的一個關係
Then go to find out the factor of this cure
那進而去找出這個治病的因素
that's funded by the government
那在政府的資助下
I don't know if I will finish in the future
我不知道將來我會不會完成
this is what they told me
這個是他們告訴我的
then if the government goes bankrupt
那如果政府破產
I don't know what will happen to this
這個就不曉得會怎麼樣
But now they are working hard
但是目前他們很努力的
to carry out such a large project
去推展這樣一個大型計畫
Then this plan was also received by many
那這個計畫也受到很多
Echoes from the hospital
醫院的迴響
So at the moment from north to south
所以在目前從北到南
There are very, very large hospitals
有非常非常多大的醫院
All medical centers are participating in this program
醫學中心全部都參入這個計畫
Then this plan is from
那這個計畫是從
2012 to 2024
2012年到2024年
Then they hope to collect 200,000
那他們希望收集20萬的
Specimens from the general public and 100,000 patients
民眾檢體和10萬病人的檢體
so everyone here
所以在座各位
If anyone is interested in this
如果有人對這個有興趣
very very hope you will
非常非常希望你們願意
To be a sample of this people
去當這個民眾的檢體
then they will help you for a long time
那他們會長期幫你們
Track your health and life
追蹤你的健康跟生活
And the data of your sample
還有你的這個檢體的這個資料
so this actually knows something about you
所以這其實對你了解
You are also very helpful personally
你個人也是非常有幫助
There are branches everywhere from south to north
從南到北在哪裡都有分店
you can go
你都可以去
tell them you want this sample
告訴他們說你要這個檢體
At the same time, an interesting thing happened
那同時間正好有一個有趣的事情發生
This Leigh-Hawaiers is from 2001
這個Leigh-Hawaiers是2001年的
Nobel Prize in Physiology
諾貝爾的生理獎
Then his important discovery is
那他重要的發現是
He found a way to control that cell cycle
他找到了一個控制那個細胞周期
Sale cycle some key elements of this molecule
Sale cycle 一些關鍵的這個分子
Then I think the Nobel Prize-winning team won the prize
那我覺得諾貝爾的得獎組在得獎之後
They seem to be starting to think
他們好像都開始想到
It's a social problem, a big problem in the world
就是社會問題 天下大問題
So he started to travel around the world
所以他就開始周遊列國
He wants to advocate a
他要提倡一個叫做
The concept of Bio-Synics
Bio-Synics 的觀念
This Bio-Synics is like a marker molecule
這個Bio-Synics 就是像標記分子一樣
He thinks that the detection of cancer or disease
他認為說癌症或者是疾病的檢測
is a very important thing
是一個非常重要的事情
is an important strategy for sustainable health
是健康永續的一個重要策略
But this requires a lot of effort
可是這個需要的努力是非常多
Less able to be done by individual labs
不太能夠由個人實驗室來做
He believes that the power of the state should be
他認為應該要由國家的力量
Production, government and education work together
產官學一起來做
So he traveled around the world
所以他就周遊列國
To promote the concept of Bio-Synics
去倡導這個Bio-Synics 的觀念
He also came to Taiwan to advocate
他也來到台灣來倡導
So later under his impetus
所以後來在他的推動之下
Washup was opened twice in Academia Sinica and Beijing Medical University
在中研院跟北醫分別開了兩次的Washup
Formally established in 2012
在2012年的時候正式成立
Because the Taiwan divine body biological database just now
因為剛剛那個台灣神體生物資料庫
Specimens have
檢體都有
So this 2002 Taiwan Barsini School
所以這個2002年的這個台灣巴爾斯妮學
hitch a ride
正好搭上順風車
You can see the five major hospitals in the first issue
你可以看到第一期過的這個五大醫院
The five major projects are all very important diseases in Taiwan
五大計畫都是台灣非常重要的病
This leader is all this doctor
這個領軍的全都是這個醫生
Expanded to 13 projects in 2013
在2013年已經擴大到13個計畫
Then I know there are 14 projects now
那我知道現在有14個計畫
This project is actually related to the Taiwan Human Biology Database
這個計畫其實跟台灣人體生物資料庫
are complementary
是相輔相成
Hoping to develop marker molecules for disease
希望能夠開發疾病的標記分子
for this important goal
為這個重要的目標
From this place, I also deeply feel that
從這個地方我也深深感受到說
In fact, most of these projects are medical teams
其實這些計畫大部分都是醫學團隊
But what is lacking is
但是比較缺的就是
Platforms for these high performance analytics
這些高效能分析的平台
Analytical talent
分析的人才
In fact, under this plan
其實在這個計畫下
i think we can go
我覺得我們是可以去
contribute our technology
貢獻我們的技術的
so i personally think
所以我個人是覺得
in Taiwan
在台灣
I'm glad we have
我很高興我們有
The Human Biodatabase
這個人體生物資料庫
With this Taiwanese Balsney
跟這個台灣巴爾斯尼卻
Our two projects can work together
我們兩個計畫能夠共同
then we hope the future
那我們希望未來
this is my personal expectation
這是我個人的期望
I always feel
我一直覺得
Many phenomena in the so-called life sciences
所謂生命科學的很多現象
In fact, many times
其實很多時候
we are a descriptive phenomenon
我們是一個描述性的現象
But from a chemical point of view
可是以化學角度
I think many things should be
我覺得應該很多東西是
countable
可以數句話的
can put this molecule
可以把這個分子
get out one by one
一個一個弄出來
so i hope
所以我自己很希望
will be able to
將來能夠
for these important diseases
針對這些重要的疾病
we can
我們能夠
not only me
不是只有我
Everyone together
大家一起
able to convert this protein
能夠把這個蛋白質
how to do messaging
如何去做訊息傳遞
able to do a digital
能夠做一個數位化
of course
那當然
there are many things that are
有很多事情是
can do
可以去做的
we hope
我們希望
Currently, except for this plan
目前除了這個計畫之下
Academician Cai Mingdao of Zhongyuan Academy
中原院蔡明道院士
Under the leadership of Academician Wang Huijun
王慧君院士的領導之下
There is also a Taiwanese protein project
還有一個台灣蛋白質計畫
I am personally responsible for the part of the protein body
我個人是負責蛋白質體的部分
We hope that with these large integrations
我們希望能夠藉由這些大型的整合
collaboration with physicians with biologists
跟醫生的合作 跟生物學家
with chemists and statisticians
跟化學家 跟統計學家
Integration of Informatics
資訊學家的整合
We want to be able to target diseases that are specific to Taiwan
我們希望能夠針對台灣特有的疾病
like i just mentioned
像我剛剛所提到的
Taiwan-specific lung cancer, breast cancer, and colon cancer
台灣特有的肺癌 乳癌 大腸致腸癌
these three diseases
這三個疾病
We hope to be able to build
我們希望能夠建立
the protein web database
這個蛋白質的網路資料庫
Once established
那一旦建立之後
our promise is
我們的承諾就是
We will put all the information
我們會把所有的資料
All are open to everyone
全部就是公開給大家使用
Then we hope that for Taiwan these
那我們希望對台灣這些
cancer development and treatment
癌症的發生跟治療
can provide more information
能夠提供比較多的資料
Let the people behind be able to do the testing
讓後面的人能夠去做檢測
or drug development
或者是做藥物的開發
But I still emphasize
不過我還是強調
it takes a long time
這需要漫長時間
I hope you have some patience
希望大家有一些耐心
what i am most interested in
那我自己最有興趣的
I am in chemistry
我自己是在化學所
Many of my colleagues are experts in drug development
我有很多同事是藥物開發的專家
So we also hope that after this network comes out,
所以我們也很希望在這個網路出來之後
We were able to find new drug target proteins
我們能夠找到新的藥物標靶蛋白
to overcome the lung cancer we were talking about
去克服我們剛所談到的肺癌
have a lot of questions
有非常多的問題
The woman with the mutation and no mutation
那個基因突變沒有突變的婦女
No targeted therapy blah blah blah
是沒有標靶療法等等等
There is also the issue of drug resistance
還有抗藥性的問題
In the end, I thank many, many friends
那最後面我謝謝很多很多的朋友
It's the kind of research that requires a lot of fields
就是這種研究需要非常多的領域
Therefore, we have four cooperation partners at Photobiological Information
所以光生物資訊我們就有四個合作對象
There are also foreign countries that I haven't listed yet.
還有國外的我還沒有列出來
we have many friends who are doctors
我們有很多醫生的朋友
There are also many SaleBioL bureaus and syntheses
還有很多SaleBioL的局跟合成
Of course, the most important thing is that I want to thank my many students
當然最重要的是我要謝謝我很多的學生
I haven't had time to put many of my new student photos in there yet.
我還來不及把我很多新學生照片擺進去
we're working hard on this
我們很努力的在做這個
We also hope to have some results in the future
我們也很希望未來有一些成果
Last but not least, I think you can see
最後面就是我想大家看得出來
this is a cell
這是一個細胞
I think in this field
我覺得在這個領域之中
it's actually very interesting very very interesting
其實很有趣 非常非常有趣
Although it is an extremely complex world
雖然它是極度複雜的一個世界
then we also hope
那我們也很希望
If any student is interested in this field
如果有學生對這個領域有興趣的
You are welcome to explore this field together
歡迎你一起來探討這個領域
then i think i'll stop here today
那我想我今天就說到這邊
thank you all
謝謝大家
I think everyone is really feasting on knowledge today
我想大家都今天真的是知識饗宴
Then we start with the most basic scientific research
那我們從最基本的科學研究
From Dr. Chen's scientific research
從陳博士的科學研究講到
The reason of your own illness and so on
你我切身的這個病的原因等等
i believe there is
我相信有
do you want to take a break or
你要休息一下嗎還是
so far so good
還好還好
If there is a problem or what can I ask you
那有問題或者什麼可以請教你
please
請
that
那個
so wonderful
這麼棒的精采
I want to ask the teacher
我想請教老師
because now it's all about triggering
因為現在都是引發
I heard that Alzheimer's is caused by the protein in the brain
聽說阿茲海默是因為頭腦裡面蛋白質
It seems like our paste
好像是像我們的那個醬糊一樣
Do you ask the teacher to say
是不是請老師說
accumulation
堆積
Please explain to the teacher
請老師說明一下
That's one big reason why Alzheimer's is happening.
就是那個阿茲海默正一個重要的原因
It's the protein structure that changes
就是那個蛋白質結構產生變化
The protein after that change
那產生變化之後那個蛋白質
They should have been there one by one.
本來應該一個一個好好的在那邊
that's because it changes
那因為它產生變化
so it all piles up
所以它全部堆積在一起
Yes, this is the reason everyone knows
對那這個是大家目前知道的原因
I know there are quite a few people
那我了解的是有蠻多人
including one of my colleagues
包括我有一位同事
that new method that they hope to develop
他們希望能夠發展的那個新的方法
able to make this process
能夠讓這個過程
able to make it reply
能夠讓它回復
no more piles
不要再產生堆積
good
好
ask the professor
請教教授
That one just mentioned the protein concentration
那個剛有提到那個蛋白質濃度
high words
高的話
the survival rate is relatively low
就是存活率比較低
Then ask the professor what to do with that
那麼請教教授那個要怎麼樣
just say yes
就說要
Does this have anything to do with what you eat?
這個跟吃什麼有沒有關係
can reduce protein concentration
能夠讓蛋白質濃度降低
The second question is
第二個問題是
DNA will
DNA會
DNA mutations create abnormalities in proteins
DNA突變會造成蛋白質的異常
then please tell me that
那請教教說那個
under what circumstances
在什麼樣的狀況下
or what causes DNA mutations
或是什麼原因會造成DNA突變
Thanks
謝謝
Let me talk about the second question first
我先講第二個問題比較單純
Many of the gene mutations come from genetics
那個基因突變很多是來自於遺傳
For example, Mediterranean flat snow
譬如說地中海形平雪
It may be more frequent on Hakka women
它可能在客家婦女上的頻率是比較高的
like EGF
像EGF
I just talked about the mutation of the gene in lung cancer
我剛剛講那個肺癌那個基因的突變
Actually we don't know why
其實我們也不知道為什麼
But the oriental mutation
但是東方人的突變
For patients, the mutation rate is as high as 60%
就病人的突變機率高達六成
But Westerners probably only have less than 20%
可是西方人就是大概只有20%不到
20%
20%
so a big difference
所以差異很大
This should be three times worse than race
這個是應該是種族的三倍差三倍
The difference between 20 and 60
20跟60的差異
So it's probably a genetic issue
所以這個應該是來自於遺傳的問題
As for what to eat for protein
至於吃什麼讓蛋白質
I'm really not an expert on this
這個我真的不是這個專家
But actually I really don't know
但是其實我真的不知道
famous, does anyone know
知名有沒有人知道
I think as far as I know it's a lot of times
我覺得就我了解是很多時候
protein changes
蛋白質會改變
In fact, except you don't eat anything
其實除了你不是吃什麼
In many cases, the influence of the environment
很多時候是環境的影響
For example, stress can also cause
譬如說壓力也會造成
Your overall physical condition, what is your metabolism?
你整個身體狀況 你的代謝什麼
that all affect each other
那都是會互相影響的
So I think it should be to maintain a healthy life schedule
所以我覺得應該是保持健康的生活作息
this should be the most important
這應該是最重要
Then what to eat? I really don’t know if there is any participation here.
那吃什麼我真的不曉得這邊有沒有參加
that doesn't move
那不動
will definitely
一定也會的
how can you do this
你怎麼可能這樣
I already understand
我已經懂了
Like I know Ah Fa Petal Protein
像我知道阿發Petal Protein
It should have nothing to do with this
跟這個應該都沒有關係
What happened when I just arrived is often like drinking
那剛來的發生很多時候是跟像喝酒
just have some living habits
就是有一些生活的習慣
Smoking increases lung cancer risk
像抽菸增加肺癌機率
already know
已經知道了
some of that may not be very clear
那有一些可能還不是很清楚
That seems to be related to drinking
那像剛才也是跟喝酒有關
And it has nothing to do with your staying up late.
還有跟你熬夜什麼這個都有關係
Yeah, so I think it should generally be
對 所以我覺得應該總的來講
or a healthy lifestyle
還是一個健康的生活態度跟
Exercise is of course one of them.
做習運動當然也是其中之一
Thank you teacher for your wonderful speech
謝謝老師精采的演講
What I want to ask is that the teacher just mentioned
我想請教的是剛剛老師有提到
Your lab has special
你的實驗室有特別做到
to notice
去注意到
for relation
for relation
leaching acidification ratio
淋酸化的比例
In fact, it has a very significant impact
其實有非常重大的影響
But the few slides in front of you
但是在你最前面的幾張投影片
already told us all
就已經告訴我們大家說
transfection followed by protein modification
轉入轉易然後蛋白質修飾
are very important parts
是很重要的幾個部分
It was also mentioned later when talking about straight floating.
那後面講直浮移的時候也有提到
You can choose whether there is acidification or saccharification
可以去選擇有沒有淋酸化有沒有糖化
So it seems that leaching acidification with or without
所以似乎淋酸化有或沒有
for your shower or other
對於你這個淋浴或是其他的
Researchers around the world should be well aware
世界各地的研究者應該很清楚
don't know why they would
那不知道為什麼他們會
didn't notice this
沒有注意到這個
And you and your lab will
而您和你的實驗室會
Why is there a way to notice this
為什麼有辦法注意到這個
Then where is the key
然後關鍵在哪裡
The other one is also what I told you today.
那另外一個也跟你們今天講的
The key is to say
有關鍵是說
You work with doctors in other fields
您跟其他領域的醫生合作
We also work with computer experts
也跟電腦的專家合作
May I ask you to cooperate
請問你們合作的
How can there be a way to cooperate
怎麼會有辦法合作的
Can you pay attention to what important generosity
能注意了哪些重要的大方
Thanks
謝謝
Okay, thank you
好 謝謝
your first question
你剛剛那個第一個問題
very important and crucial
非常的重要跟關鍵
should mean
應該是說
That is to say, people in the field of protein geology
就是說蛋白質地學這個領域的人
When analyzing protein zero acidification
在分析蛋白質零酸化的時候
Because it is the inner segment Peptide with zero acidification
因為它是把有零酸化的內段Peptide
or Protin to extract it
或Protin把它萃取出來
So we're doing proteomic analysis
所以我們在做蛋白質體學分析
Often we just like to compare
常常是我們就喜歡比來比去
sick or not
有病沒病比
or whether there is stimulation or no stimulation
或是有刺激沒刺激
So everyone is comparing
所以大家都在比的是
Triple or Triple
增加兩倍還是減少兩倍
but we only know
可是我們只知道
Altogether tripled
總而來講增加兩倍
You don't know this twice because
你不知道這兩倍是因為
Possibly increased protein concentration
有可能蛋白質濃度增加
so you double
所以你增加兩倍
However, the degree of zero acidification remains the same
可是零酸化程度不變
It is also possible that the protein concentration does not change
也有可能是蛋白質濃度不變
But zero acidification triples
可是零酸化程度增加兩倍
Before our method
在我們這個方法之前
Everyone doesn't make a difference
大家不太有區分
Then we thought of a way
那後來我們就想了一個方法
Let's change the concentration
我們去把濃度的改變
with protein changes
跟蛋白質的改變
we can see at the same time
我們可以同時看得出來
we just stumbled upon
我們才無意中發現
I'm also surprised
我也蠻驚訝的
because I always feel
因為我一直覺得
Changes in protein concentration
蛋白質濃度改變
should be more important
應該是比較重要的事情
in that experiment
就在那個實驗中
we discover
我們發現
Those proteins have not changed
那些蛋白質竟然都不變
fantastic
很奇妙
As for the second question
那至於第二個問題
good question
好問題
I tell my own experience
我講我自己經驗
Because I am a very casual person
因為我是一個很隨性的人
Then I usually run into problems
那我通常是遇到問題
I will solve it
我才會去解決
Then why did you start cooperating with the news?
那為什麼會開始跟資訊合作
because in the early
是因為在早期
When we first analyze
我們先是在做分析的時候
Computers were not good at that time
那個時候電腦不太會
So we're gonna make protein firm
所以我們要做蛋白質堅定
To send data to the Internet
要把資料送到網路上去
send it to the internet
那送到網路上
I don't know can't keep sending and sending
我不知道不可以一直送一直送
The website that was sent later
就後來那個送的那個網站
think we're hackers
覺得我們是駭客
They obviously did not notify the network administrator of our Chemical Institute
就顯意沒有通知我們化學所的網管
said to take us
說要把我們
is the one that won't let us use
就是那個不讓我們使用
say we are hackers
說我們是駭客
Then I thought it was serious
後來我就覺得是事情很嚴重
can't go on like this
就不能再這樣下去
Then I happened to meet at Academia Sinica
然後我正好在中研院遇到
I met a middle school classmate from my elementary school in the parking lot
停車場遇到一個我小學的國中同學
He happened to be in teacher Xu Wennian's doctoral class
他正好是許文年老師的博士班
Postdoc
Postdoc
Then I asked him
然後我就問他說
I was recently lodged by that Brock from NCBI
我最近被 NCBI那個Brock 住
Could you please write a small program
可不可以請你們幫忙寫個小程式
So we usually cooperate in the midst of the problem
所以我們通常是在問題之中去合作
But there is a very important key
但是有一個很重要的關鍵就是
You must be able to understand his language
你一定要能夠了解他的語言
You can't talk to a doctor to learn a language
你不能跟醫生說話學語言
he can't understand
他是聽不懂的
you have to speak his language
你要講他的語言
it takes time
那這些都很需要時間
Then how about counting the results
然後要不能計較那個成果
That is to say like we...
就是說像我們...
Excuse me
不好意思
That is, I think a good cooperation is to
就是我覺得一個好的合作就是要
special...
非常的...
open minded
open minded
For example, information paper
譬如說資訊的paper
It's a very real problem
就是這是很現實的問題
It's who does the communication
就是通訊做的是誰
I usually don't hang up
我通常都不掛
even if i help write
即使我幫忙寫
Because this is their credit
因為這個是他們的credit
Then I think everyone should be able to share
那我覺得大家要能夠去分享
Common results
共同的成果
this is very important
這是很重要
What's more, you need to communicate frequently
那還有就是你要常常溝通
Then I have a very lively personality
那我個性是很活潑的個性
So I like to talk to people
所以就是很喜歡跟人家講話
Yes, and my students are also important.
對 那還有我的學生也很重要
That is, my students are willing to work with them
就是我的學生很願意去跟他們合作
that medicine you must
那醫學你一定要
is what I said must
就是我講的一定要
because doctors are busy
因為醫生都很忙
They have free time to chat with you over there
他們有空跟你在那邊東扯西扯
so you must know his language very well
所以你一定要非常了解他的語言
Then you have to be able to say the same thing as him
然後你要能夠跟他講一樣的話
he will do it with you
他才會跟你一起弄
I don't think it's that difficult
那我覺得這些其實沒有那麼困難
But you just have to be willing to take the time to
但是你就是要願意花時間去
It will be fine after a long time
那久了以後就好
Because when I went to the hospital of traditional Chinese medicine, actually
因為我到中醫院的時候其實
I have never heard of an amino acid
我沒有聽過什麼叫安基酸
my students know
我學生都知道
Poetin protein heard
Poetin蛋白質聽過
But I don’t know Poetin means protein
可是Poetin我不曉得就是蛋白質的意思
But because the life sciences of Zhongyuan Institute are too strong
但是因為中原院的生命科學太強了
So after a long time, I learned like this
所以久了以後就學起來了這樣
Teacher thank you for your wonderful speech
老師謝謝您的精采的演講
I have a question for your last mention of BioBank
我有個問題是針對您最後提到的BioBank
I think BioBank is a very Promise project
BioBank我覺得是一個很Promise的計畫
Because Chronic disease is a headache for everyone
因為Chronic disease 慢性病是大家一層頭痛的問題
And the problem of global aging that we are now facing
而且現在要面臨的全球老齡化的問題
Whether it is a developing country or a developing country
不管是開發中國家或者是在以開發國家
Aging is a serious problem
老齡化都是一個很嚴重的問題
And then it's very relevant to chronic diseases
然後這跟慢性病又是很相關性的
So BioBank
所以BioBank
I think it's pretty good that we developed this
我覺得我們發展這個是蠻不錯的
For the future of Taiwan, whether it is the development of the biotechnology industry
對台灣未來不管是生技產業的發展
Or academic development is very good
或是學術上發展是很不錯
But teacher, you also mentioned earlier
但是老師您早先時間的時候也提到
The concept of BioBank comes from BioSignature
BioBank這個概念是從BioSignature來的
No, because BioBank can first
不是,因為BioBank可以先的
OK, that's because in short my question is BioSignature
OK,那因為總之我的問題是BioSignature
It is still being promoted
竟然現在還在一直被推廣
What about our so-called global competitors?
那我們所謂的全球的競爭對手
or who the partner is
或者是合作夥伴是誰
is someone
就是有誰
Where are similar things being done
哪些地方也有在做類似的事情
Because like our national fitness database
因為像我們的全民健跑資料庫
Actually a good Ball Bank too
事實上也是一個很好的Ball Bank
But this is what we are
但是這也是我們現在
Another good opportunity from the opening
開業出來的另外一個利機
But who else is our competitor?
但是我們競爭對手到底是還有誰
not to compete now
現在不是要競爭
You know that the era of globalization is called cooperation
你知道現在全球化的時代叫合作
I'll give an example
我舉例子好了
Like we do that cancer tissue thing
像我們做那個癌症組織這件事
We are cooperating with NCI in the United States
我們是跟美國的NCI合作
Why
為什麼
Because our lung cancer is a mutation of EGA
因為我們的肺癌是EGA化的Mutation
Their lung cancer is a mutation of Carousal
他們的肺癌是Carousal的Mutation
The two sides happen to be the control group
兩邊正好是對照組
so we cooperate
所以我們是合作的
So now at least I have a lot of experience
所以現在至少我的經驗很多
Even though the mainland has been suppressing us
即使說大陸一直打壓我們
But in fact they still put us
可是其實他們還是把我們
as a partner
當一個合作對象
I'm still the same
那同樣的我還是
because you are young
因為你們是年輕人
i still want to talk
我還是要講
Of course, Taiwan's resources
就是當然台灣的資源
with foreign superpowers
跟國外那些超級大國
Support to the mainland
向大陸支援
is very rich
是非常豐富
But if you open your heart a little
可是如果你自己心胸打開一點
you befriend them
你跟他們當朋友
they'll treat you like a friend
他們就會把你當朋友
So I think cooperation is the way of the future
所以我覺得合作才是未來的路
that's like competition
那像競爭這件事情
like felay i don't think we have any competition
像費萊我不覺得我們有什麼競爭
Taiwan is doing very well
台灣做得非常好
that Ganglai's words
那剛萊的話
I'm afraid there will be some competition
恐怕會有一些競爭
Because the mainland is Ganglai for them
因為大陸是以剛萊為他們
biggest biggest goal
最大最大的目標
But Taiwan has Taiwan's advantages
可是台灣有台灣的優勢
Yes, I think in Taiwan
對 那我覺得在台灣
we just go
我們就是走
I feel like I'm going to be a little girl
我自己是覺得走小兒妹
so i don't just do that
所以我不會就是做那種
It doesn't take a lot of resources
非要很多很多資源的
Of course I still need some resources
當然我還是要一些資源
I want to talk to Deputy Wang
要跟王副講
But you can't use that
但是你沒有辦法用那種
Why did Zhifu fight with them when buying ingredients?
什麼一次買食材 執腐跟他們拼了
the impossible
那個不可能的事
The mainland buys 100 units at a time
大陸一次買一百台
how do you fight him
你怎麼跟他拼
he is an institute
他是一個研究所
then i'm just a person
然後我只是一個個人
you can't fight him
你沒有辦法跟他拼
So what you have to do is
所以你一定要去做的是
Taiwan has an advantage
我們台灣有優勢的
So why do we do Philae and Breast Cancer?
那為什麼我們會做費萊跟乳癌
In fact, it was discussed with the court
其實是有跟院討論過的
Because we have breast cancer in Philae
因為我們有在費萊乳癌方面
there are many
都有非常多的
powerful expert
強大的專家
Shen Zhiyang's own breast cancer is doing very well
那沈志揚本身乳癌做得非常好
And Vice President Chen Jianren is also
還有陳建仁副院長也是
What about lung cancer
那肺癌的話
Principal Yang Panshi should be at the top of the world
楊潘石校長應該全世界很前面的
so i think this
所以我覺得這個
You just have to take advantage of Taiwan
你只要利用台灣的優勢
don't worry about competition
不用擔心競爭
The problem with competition is
那競爭的問題就是
We students and our own time should be faster
我們學生我們自己時間要快一點
so
這樣
Yes, hear no students behind
對 聽到沒有學生在後面
Teacher, what do you mean
老師那您的意思是說
Like our Bao Bank
像我們Bao Bank
we are not alone
我們不是只是單單的
is to focus on chronic patients
就是專注在慢性病人上面
I'm also special
我還特別的就是
Focus more on lung cancer and breast cancer
更專心的在肺癌跟乳癌上面
Actually I didn't let it go
其實我沒有放
But if you want to see there is
但是你要看的話有
Actually quite sick
其實蠻多病的是
i took it off
我把它拿掉了
just a lot of sickness
就是蠻多病
many cancers have
很多癌症都有
then new blood vessels
然後新血管
like just asked
像剛剛問的
Alzheimer's Disease Wang Chujun
埃斯海默症王楚軍
They are all in the plan
他們都是在這個計劃之中
very many diseases
非常非常多的病
Not just chronic diseases
不是只有慢性病而已
Yes, the whole world is not only our Taiwan
對 那全球就是不是只有我們台灣
In collecting this so-called age-based
在蒐集這種所謂的依據年紀
and keep track of them
然後不斷去追蹤他們
many places have
很多地方都有
I know it's like Europe
我了解的是像歐洲
they have a very large
他們有一個非常龐大的
Then they also recently asked
然後他們最近也在問說
Should Taiwan participate?
台灣要不要參加
But something from Taiwan
可是台灣的東西
As far as Taiwan's regulations are
就台灣的法規是
Simplified cannot be sent out
簡體不能送出去
so there is no way
所以後來就沒辦法
The one in the European Union is
歐盟的那個是
They can be exported in simplified form
他們簡體是可以輸出來的
So if I join that league today
所以如果今天我參加那個聯盟
I can apply Simplified to analyze
我可以去申請簡體來分析
European Union
歐盟
That's also in Hupo
那也是在Hupo
As for the Hupo I just mentioned
就我剛剛講的Hupo下
We have signed the MOU
我們已經簽了MOU了
Then Japan also has this small database
那日本也有這個小型的這些資料庫
There are also some in Japan
也是有一些 日本也有
other places
那其他地方
I think Taiwan
我覺得台灣這個
Should be quite large
應該算規模很大的
So I think this is a Taiwanese
所以我覺得這是台灣一個
very important asset
非常重要的資產
right
對
The one in Japan has been in business for 50 years
像日本那個是已經經營了50年
So I told Shen Zhiyang
所以我就跟沈志洋說
You better live another 50 years
你最好要繼續再活50年
to support this database
才能撐著這個資料庫
50 years old
50年的
If you want to track a group
就你想追蹤一個族群
50 years is not easy
50年喔 非常不容易
that's a very important asset
那是很重要很重要的資產
May I ask the professor, how does cancer arise?
請問教授 癌症是怎麼產生的
Thanks
謝謝
Maybe I'm not the best person to answer
可能我不是最適合回答的耶
is there any
這邊有沒有
Maybe we should invite Principal Yang Tengci to explain
可能要請楊叛慈校長來講解
I say it like this
我這樣講好了
There are many, many causes of cancer
癌症的成因非常非常多
That is, it may be like the mutation of the gene I just mentioned
就是它有可能像我剛剛講的那個基因的突變
A genetic change is a
基因的變化是一個
like many so-called autocancers
像很多所謂的自癌
Genes that cause cancer are well known
導致癌症的基因是很多都知道的
that protein will also
那 protein 也會
But in the end then this happened
可是到底 然後這個發生原因
related to environmental factors
跟環境因子有關
like i just said about smoking
像我剛剛講抽菸
And that one, a woman who gave birth to a D child very late.
還有那個 就是很晚生D胎的女性
Cancer is relatively intense is high
癌症相對激烈是高
many environmental factors
就很多環境的因子
but if you want to ask
可是如果你要問說
Which is the main reason
哪一個是最主要的原因
no standard answer
沒有標準答案
Like that Lee Harvey just now
像剛剛那個李哈威
when he came to taiwan
他來台灣的時候
We held a careful workshop
我們開了一個小心的研討會
Then I asked him
然後我就問他說
because they america do everything
因為他們美國什麼都做
This gene sports also do
這個基因體育也做
Agents also do
代賣體也做
do everything
什麼什麼都做
ask him
問他說
Which is the most important molecule in nature
自然最重要的分子是哪一個
he said his statement was funny
他說他的說法很有趣
He said that so far there is no standard answer
他說目前為止沒有標準答案
so everyone doesn't know
所以大家都不曉得
So each one should be done
所以應該每一個都要做
this is his answer
這是他的回答
So there are many causes of his cancer
所以他癌症的成因是非常多的
that seems to have a theory that says
那像有一個理論是說
you have some so-called cancer stem cells in your body
你在身體中有一些所謂的癌症幹細胞
he hides over there
他隱藏在那邊
Then when environmental factors come out
然後當環境因子出來的時候
he is activated
他就被活化
There is also such a saying
也有這樣的說法
May ask Yang to rebel
可能要請楊叛詞
He is better suited to answer this question
他比較適合回答這個問題
this professor chen
這個陳教授
you start researching
你從開始研究
I've been thinking about it now, there's no skipped stitches
我一直想到現在 都沒有跳針
And the speech and the setting are all normal.
而且講話那個樹立 都很正常
Didn't start coughing until 93 minutes
到93分鐘才開始咳嗽
then i want to ask a question now
那我現在要請教一個問題
ask a question
請教一個問題
Now we know all about Genesis
現在我們對基因普我們都知道
But cancer is still a mystery
但是癌症還是一個謎
Maybe we have a better understanding of the topic we just talked about
說不定我們對剛才講的題目
protein analysis
蛋白質的分析
Come as once Hanayama cancer time
來作為一旦花山癌症的時候
It is more reliable to track its treatment
追蹤其治療還是比較來得可靠
is it possible
是不是有可能
We are now old people looking forward to
我們現在人老的期待
Inside this protein study
裡面這個蛋白質的研究
more thorough words
更透徹的話
Huashan who can control this cancer
可以掌控這個癌症的花山
is it possible
是不是有這種可能
of course it is possible
當然有可能
We'd love to get to this point
我們很希望能達到這一步
so we're doing some
所以我們有在做一些
just doing some analysis
就是在做一些分析
For example, when we first arrived
譬如說我們在剛來
We have some cooperation with Academician Chen Peizhe
我們跟陳培哲院士有一些合作
We hope that with Teacher Yang Fuliang
我們希望其實跟楊富亮老師
some are doing together
有的是一起在做的
It is hoped that some molecules can be found in the blood of newly arrived patients for testing
就是希望說從剛來的病人血液中找到一些分子做檢測
Then Teacher Yang Fuliang and the others are doing the super fast one
然後楊富亮老師他們在做那種超快速那個
Reagents that can be tested at home
在家都可以檢測的試劑
that small instrument
的那種那個儀器小小
That's not good at talking
那叫什麼都不太會講
kit
kit
right
對
Am looking forward to
很期待
and certification
還有認證
right
對
We would love to be able to reach the internal
我們很希望能夠達到內部
so we should have that
所以我們應該要那個
Find that Guo Dong through the relationship
通過關係找那個郭董
Guo Dong today more than 100 National Taiwan University to do IZEN
郭董今天那一百多個台大做IZEN
Why not come and do our blank paper research
就還不如來做我們這個當白紙的研究
actually
其實
In fact, I think there are some three-season industries over there.
其實我覺得有一些三季產業是有在那邊
but
但是
I think it's a pity
我覺得比較可惜
sorry to say
遺憾的是說
Taiwan's biotech industry is small
台灣生技產業規模很小
So they make sure you develop it to a very mature stage
所以他們一定要你研發到非常成熟階段
For example, five hundred people
譬如說做了五百個人
The result is very sure that they are willing to become a class
成果非常確定他們才願意成階
At the very early stage of so-called development
那在很早期這種所謂開發型的階段
no one wants to give you money
沒有人要給你錢
The Central Plains Institute is willing to give us the
中原院願意給我們經北
thank you very much tonight
今天晚上非常謝謝你
Thanks
謝謝
You are probably doomed to eat more when you are born
你一生出來大概就注定你可以吃多的
You ate too much earlier, you just explained
你早吃得多你就說明的
eat less
吃得少就說明
Did my professor just say a statistic
是不是我教授剛才有說一個數據
Is it right now that I read some books
是不是現在我看一些書
He said that a person is born like a car
就是他說一個人生出來就像汽車一樣
You probably use a lot of connections
你大概使用連線多的
probably fixed
大概都固定了
You just say about this
你只要說大概這個關
Is there a corresponding saying that a person is like this
是不是有相應說一個人這樣
You can roughly explain or eat too much has a fixed
你就大概說明或者吃多的都有固定
Because I can still calculate this data
因為這數據我還是可以算出來
This is probably not possible from a scientific point of view.
這個大概目前以科學角度大概沒辦法
but i can only say
但是我只能講說
You take good care of your body, take care of your daily routine and do a good job
你把身體好好顧好生活作息做好
it must be ok
這一定是OK的
Of course another angle is
那當然另外一個角度是
I'm still full of trust in things I can't see
我還滿相信一些看不見的事情
There are things that science can't explain
有科學無法解釋的事情
man's fate
人的宿命人的一生
Is it a well-structured network?
是不是架構好的一個網路
I personally believe it
我個人其實是相信的
it's not science
這不是科學
This is not the angle of the flaming meatball
這不是炎肉圓的角度
Yes but in this way
對 但是以這個方法
That is to say, use this biochemical method to do this thing
就是說用這種生化的方法來做這件事情
currently there is no way
目前是沒辦法
We can only measure these
我們只能在測量這些
Whether protein or gene
不管是蛋白質或基因
It actually just tells you an instant status
它其實只是告訴你一個即時的狀態
that sample
就是那個樣品
Or if I draw your blood now
或者是我現在如果抽你血
I will test
我來測
I just detected your current state
我只是測到你現在這個狀態
but i can't tell you
但是我沒有辦法告訴你
what's your future
你未來會怎麼樣
or how you used to be
或者是你過去怎麼樣
We can only measure your current state
我們只能測到你現在的狀態
So this problem is still rare
所以這個問題還是難得
You seem to be talking about the world of spirits, right?
你是好像就是說有靈的世界是吧
that too big effect
那個太大效果
you laugh so hard that he thinks
你笑得他是想
There is also something about listening to the professor
聽教授講的事也有
also believe so
也相信這樣
i like to read some other books
我喜歡看一些其他的書
I can't say too much about my identity today
今天的身份不太能講太多
It's okay, professor, I'll ask for advice
沒事 教授我請教
So what we just mentioned is
這樣我們剛剛在提到的都是
The professor has about this software data analysis aspect
教授有關於這個軟體數據分析方面
So we are currently in Taiwan to test
那麼我們在台灣在目前就是去檢測
For example, Mr. Tanaka
比如說像田中先生那個
Mr. Donnakar, they pour gold
唐納卡先生他們那個倒金
What is worth the capabilities of this developed technology
什麼都值得這種開發的技術的能力
Has our current Taiwan caught up?
我們台灣現在的有沒有跟上來
when you are researching
那你們在研究的時候
In the use of this instrument is there
在這個儀器的使用有沒有
That's what they're making
就是這個他們推陳出新的
Has been making analysis faster and more accurate
一直在讓分析更快更精準
In fact, this problem is our field
其實這個問題是我們這個領域
a big challenge
一個很大的挑戰
Because the cost of paper Puyi is actually quite expensive
因為紙樸移的造價其實還滿昂貴的
a general instrument
一台一般型的儀器
Maybe 20 to 30 million
可能兩千萬三千萬都有
So when your instrument comes out
所以當你儀器的出陳推新
continue
持續一直持續
But from an academic point of view
可是以學界的角度
Unlikely to keep buying new instruments
不太可能一直買新的儀器
so our
所以我們的
My own thoughts are usually
我自己的想法通常就是
what equipment do i have
我有什麼儀器
what instrument do i use
我就用什麼儀器
Then what we hope is from
那我們希望的是從
Maybe go from the methodology side
也許從前面方法學那邊去
go do it well
去好好地把它做好
Of course, if Academia Sinica supports us very much
那當然如果中研院很支持我們
or the country is very supportive of us
或國家很支持我們
Give us constantly new instruments
給我們不斷新的儀器
that is of course ideal
那當然是最理想
But I think Taiwan resources
可是我覺得以台灣資源
Going to talk to people like the United States or the mainland
要去跟像美國或大陸這種
keep buying keep buying
一直買一直買
we may have a little difficulty
我們大概會有點困難
that information
那資訊方面
In fact, Taiwan's information is very strong
其實台灣的資訊很強
I think Taiwan's information is very strong
我覺得台灣資訊很強
Like our analysis software
像我們那個分析那個軟體
Teacher Song Deyi Teacher Xu Weinian
宋定義老師 許惟年老師
their software
他們那個軟體
that is very
那個是非常
That is, the level of analysis is very good
就是分析的程度是非常好
I think the whole world
我覺得那全世界
Must be the first few
一定是排前面幾個
Then there's that big data
那還有那種大數據
It is also a powerful
也是台灣的一個強效
So I think bioinformatics in Taiwan
所以我覺得生物資訊在台灣
In fact, we can make good use of it
其實是我們可以好好利用的
an advantage
一個優勢
As for the salary of the instrument
那至於儀器的推薪
Or in Zhipuyi's research and development
或是在直普一的研發
Actually in Taiwan
其實在台灣
some people are doing
有一些人在做
Like Chen Zhongxuan and Academician Chen of Genome Center of Central Plains Institute
像中原院基因體中心陳仲軒、陳院士
He has done a very good job in the research and development of Zhipuyi
他在植普醫的研發是做得非常非常的好
There is also a researcher Wang Yisheng
還有一個王藝生研究員
He is also doing instrument research and development
他也是做儀器的研發
well done too
也是做得非常好
Today, it is also mentioned that he only started at 93 minutes
今天也是就講到他是93分鐘才開始
I'm coughing now
現在已經開始咳嗽了
let us thank chen
讓我們謝謝陳
thank you all
謝謝大家